<?xml version="1.0" encoding='iso-8859-1'?>
<document>
	<properties>
	        <author email="vast@ebi.ac.uk">Volker Ast</author>
	        <title>Ontology Edit Service (OES) specification</title>
	</properties>
	
	<body>	
		
		<section name="Introduction">
		<p>
		This document gives an overview over the planed functions, internal processes and the database
		schema of the Ontology Edit Service (OES) tool. By using the OES tool, the user will be able to upload, edit, save and 
		export an ontology in OBO format. 
		</p>
		</section>
		
		<section name="Content">
         <ul>
            <li><a href="#Functions_overview">OES style and functions</a></li>
            <li><a href="#Workflow_diagrams">Workflow diagrams</a></li>
            <li><a href="#Database_schema">Database schema</a></li>                        
         </ul>
       </section>		
		
		<section name="OES style and functions">
			<a name="Functions_overview"></a>
			<p>
			The following PPT presentation gives an idea how the OES tool will look like and what
			functions will be available. 
			</p>
			<a href="../images/oesSpecification/Ontology_Edit_Service_Outline.ppt">OES outline.</a>			
		
		</section>
		
		<section name="Workflow diagrams">
			<a name="Workflow_diagrams"></a>
			<p>
			A detailed description of the used data and its workflow can be seen in the shown workflow diagrams.
			There are graphics for the procedures Ontology Upload, Term Search, Edit Term and Manage Ontology.
			</p>
			<subsection name="Ontology Upload">
			<img src="../images/oesSpecification/File_Upload.bmp" alt="File Upload"> </img>
			</subsection>
			
			<subsection name="Term Search">
			<img src="../images/oesSpecification/Term_Search.bmp" alt="Term Search"> </img>
			</subsection>
			
			<subsection name="Edit Term">
			<img src="../images/oesSpecification/Edit_Term.bmp" alt="Edit Term"> </img>
			</subsection>
			
			<subsection name="Manage Ontology">
			<img src="../images/oesSpecification/Manage_Ontology.bmp" alt="Manage Ontology"> </img>
			</subsection>
		
		</section>
	   	
	   	<section name="Database schema">
			<a name="Database_schema"></a>
			<p>
			The OES tool is based on the following database schema. This is similar to the schema
			of the Ontology Lookup Service (OLS) but has several extensions in the tables "dbxref",
			 "term", "annotation", "term_synonym" and "ontology". Furthermore it has three additional 
			 tables "users", "term_access"  and "ontology_user".
			 </p>
			 <img src="../images/oesSpecification/OES_Table_Schema_Cleaned.gif" alt="OES Table Schema"> </img>
			 <p>
			The tables "term", "annotation", "term_synonym" and "dbxref" have been extended by the additional 
			attributes "modified_by", "modified_at", "created_by" and "created_at". This should provide a traceability
			to find out who created or modified which term, dbxref, annotation or synonym in a certain ontology and when. <br/>
			The "ontology" table has the extra attributes "status", which can be either private or public and 
			"allow_cycles", which indicates whether an ontology can contain cycles, i.e. a term could be linked to an ancestor term. <br/>
			The additional table "users" contains information about registered users like name, password, email and company.			
			The role of each user is determined in the "ontology_user" table, where a certain user can be either 
			adminstrator or user of a certain ontology. Administrators have total access to their ontology(s)
			and can give registered users access to a certain range of their ontology. This range is defined in the
			table "term_access", where a certain user identified by his/her ID has access to the range specified by
			the "term_id", i.e. all the terms which are direct or indirect descendants of this term.
			</p>
		</section>
	   
	</body>			
</document>