<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<document>

    <properties>
        <author email="rafalcan@ebi.ac.uk">Rafael Alcántara</author>
        <title>Specification for enhancement of IntEnz reactions</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <div class="">Rhea is a biochemical reactions database already in
            production, result of this specification.</div>

       <section name="Table Of Contents">
         <ul>
            <li><a href="#Current_status">Current status and problems to solve</a></li>
            <li><a href="#Goals">Goals</a></li>
            <li><a href="#Existing_reaction">Existing reaction databases and data models</a></li>
            <li><a href="#Potential_external">Potential external users of enhanced IntEnz reactions</a></li>
            <li><a href="#Use-cases">Use-cases</a></li>
            <li><a href="#Requirements">Requirements</a></li>
            <li><a href="#Influence">Influence on existing systems</a></li>
            <li><a href="#Conclusions">Conclusions</a></li>
            <li><a href="#Timetable">Timetable</a></li>
         </ul>
       </section>
        <a name="Current_status"/>
        <section name="Current status and problems to solve" id="currentStatus">
            <img src="../../../images/reactionsSpec/reactionsDbCurrentStatus.png"
                 alt="reactions in the current DB schema"/>
            <p>IntEnz includes one or more reactions per enzyme entry, as free
                text. Those reactions have no unique identifiers, so if two
                enzymes catalyze the same reaction, that means two rows in the
                database containing the same equation string
                (<i>redundancy</i>).
                <br/>
                Reactions are ordered for an enzyme entry with multiple
                reactions, but there is currently no way to distinguish reaction
                steps and alternative reactions (<i>ambiguity</i>).
                <br/>
                The string of characters which defines the equation has no link
                to other databases for reactants and products
                (<i>isolation</i>).
                <br/>
                Enzyme entries have a unique EC number which can eventually
                change due to transfer or splitting. Besides, the curator tool
                architecture assigns them an internal unique identifier which
				changes whenever the entry changes its status
                (<i>instability</i>).
            </p>
        </section>

        <a name="Goals"/>
        <section name="Goals">
            <ul>
                <li>Use a <b>controlled vocabulary of small molecules</b>
                    available from <b><a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/chebi">ChEBI
                    </a></b> and map IntEnz reactions (reactants and products)
                    and cofactors to it. To that end, the current reaction
                    and cofactor text will be parsed, extracting the names of
                    compounds which will be mapped to ChEBI.</li>
                <li><b>Stable and unique public identifiers</b> for reactions.
                    Once achieved, it will be feasible to develop stable public
                    identifiers for the enzyme entries themselves.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <a name="Existing_reaction"/>
        <section name="Existing reaction databases and data models">
        <!-- Benefits and drawbacks/ will they fit into our data structure -->
           <subsection name="Databases">
            <ul>
                <li><a href="http://www.reactome.org/"><b>Reactome</b></a> has
                    a different concept of reaction and enzyme compared to
                    IntEnz. It takes into account the <i>compartment</i> where
                    reactants and products are, and the <i>species</i> where
                    reactions are found. Besides, reactions are also considered
                    different because of their <i>catalyst</i>, which map to one
                    UniProt entry at most.<br/>
                    IntEnz, following NC-IUBMB design, considers a reaction as
                    unique independently of the compartment, species or concrete
                    catalyzing protein.
                    <ul>
                       <li>Database: Reactome uses the mySQL database and is pretty much tied to it
                       via different constraints. It uses a non-traditional approach to load its
                       schema from the database in that the schema is recreated from a 'schema_table'
                       in the database. The traditional approach used by most EBI databases is to design
                       tables and domain models that correspond, then use a mapping tool such as OJB,
                       Toplink or JDBC to map the tables to the domain model. This is not done in Reactome
                       this way because they anticipate many changes to their schema.<br/>
                       <table>
                          <tr><th>Advantages</th><th>Disadvantages</th></tr>
                       <tr>
                          <td>Generic schema format which could in theory map to any domain model.
                          </td>
                          <td>Non standard approach of database design - which means only a few specialised
                          people could support it.</td>
                       </tr>
                       <tr>
                          <td>--
                          </td>
                          <td>Would require us to move to MySQL - which would cost a minimum
                          5 months full time development to move all our PL/SQL procedures developed
                          for IntEnz. IntEnz does not using any generic mapping tools like Toplink or OJB
                          so all the JDBC would need to be converted which would require a major revamp.</td>
                       </tr>
                          <tr>
                          <td>--
                          </td>
                          <td>Long term maintenance of this project would be at risk as mySQL is not
                          officially supported by any DBA's in our group.</td>
                       </tr>
                       </table><br/>
                       </li>
                       <li>Curator tool: Reactome has developed a standalone curator tool which uses
                       the JAVA swing framework. The tool is dependent on using the database schema
                       setup as described above. It is maintained by one developer based at the EBI.
                          The tool loads in a schema setup based on the database table 'schema_table'.
                          It then generates the domain model from this. It extracts an entry from the
                          database and loads it locally for the curator to use. This is kind of a like
                          a CVS facility. For any specialised treatment such as validation of the data you need to have
                          utility classes. The tool has no validation for reactions which is a component
                          we are desperately searching for.
                          <table>
                          <tr><th>Advantages</th><th>Disadvantages</th></tr>
                       <tr>
                          <td>Existing tool which is succesfully used in production by another group at the EBI.
                          </td>
                          <td>The tool is dependent on the database schema as described above. According
                          to the developer if we deviate from using the generic database schema setup it would
                          require a major revamp of the tool and in his opinion it would not be worth it.</td>
                       </tr>
                       <tr>
                          <td>Using standard JAVA which is supported in our group.
                          </td>
                          <td>The validations which are currently done could cause a maintenance headache.
                          Currently all validations are done via the STRUTS validation framework which
                          ties in all the data neatly.</td>
                       </tr>
                          <tr>
                          <td>The CVS facility is a great feature.
                          </td>
                          <td>Again the long term maintenance of this tool would be slightly worrying
                          due to their non-standard approach to design. It is much easier to hire a
                          developer who knows the STRUTS framework rather than a specific non-standard database
                          tool.</td>
                       </tr>
                             <tr>
                          <td>--
                          </td>
                          <td>Using tool would require some major rework and it does not make sense in
                          the light that IntEnz already has a specialised curator tool with all the enzyme
                          functionality in it. The IntEnz curator tool is stable and has been in production
                          for over a year, in addition the curators are finally happy with it.</td>
                       </tr>
                       </table><br/>
                       </li>
                    </ul>
                    </li>
                <li><a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/thornton-srv/databases/MACiE/">
                    <b>MACiE</b></a> deals with enzymatic reaction mechanisms,
                    which means taking into account the protein structure (PDB
                    and CATH data). That is out of the scope of IntEnz.<br/>
                    As stated before, IntEnz reactions can't be different
                    because of the catalyzing protein. MACiE reactions are.
                    </li>
<!--
                <li><a href="http://www.brenda.uni-koeln.de/"><b>BRENDA</b></a>
                    </li>
 -->
                <li><a href="http://www.genome.ad.jp/kegg/reaction/">
                    <b>KEGG</b></a> has public reaction ids. Reactions are
                    decomposed into reactants and products, with links to the
                    corresponding KEGG compounds. The database can be
                    searched - by reaction, compound or enzyme - using
                    webservices and a
                    <a href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/soap/support/keggapi.jar">
                    jar file</a> they provide. There is also a
                    <a href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/soap/doc/keggapi_manual.html">
                    user manual</a> available.<br/>
                    Although the KEGG reaction database will provide a very good
                    validation and cross-reference source we are unable to use
                    it because it does not contain the strict CV formatting
                    requirements which is a must for IntEnz.<br/>
                    However, we plan to use the KEGG reactions as an integral validation resource
                   and also ease our cross mapping to reactions via the EC numbers.
                    </li>
              </ul>
               </subsection>
           <subsection name="Data Models">
           <ul>
                <li><a href="http://sbml.org/"><b>SBML</b></a>: the Systems
                    Biology Markup Language is becoming a standard format
                    for describing biochemical reaction networks. Based on XML
                    and other XML standards (MathML, CellML), it is used by an
                    increasing number of applications and databases
                    (<a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomodels">BioModels</a> and
                    <a href="http://reactome.org">Reactome</a> among others).
                    <br/>
                    SBML is not a database schema. Taken from the SBML FAQ:
                    <br/>
                    <i>There is no reason why SBML models could not be stored in
                    a database, nor is there any reason why you could not use
                    SBML as a schema. However, this was not the motivation for
                    creating SBML. An SBML model is meant to encode a consistent
                    view of knowledge of a biological system.</i>
                    <br/>
                    As BioPAX, SBML will be considered as as an import/export
                    format for IntEnz reactions. To this end, there exist a
                    <a href="http://jigcell.biol.vt.edu/jigcell/docs/SBML/index.html">
                    jar file</a> by JigCell to read/write SBML level 2.
                    </li>
                <li><a href="http://www.biopax.org"><b>BioPAX</b></a>
                    is a collaborative effort to create a data exchange format
                    for biological pathway data using the OWL language.
                    Though it tries to represent the same type of data as
                    SBML, they differ in their views being BioPAX more
                    qualitative, cross-reference and ontology-oriented, and SBML
                    more quantitative and mathematics-oriented. Far from being
                    incompatible, they can be mixed in the same XML document.
                    <br/>
                    BioPAX uses known standards, including pointers to GO, CML
                    instances and SMILES format.
                    <br/>
                    The <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/jastor/">Jastor
                    project</a> offers automatically generated APIs for several
                    ontologies from their OWL files, among others a BioPAX API.
                    <br/>
                    BioPAX will be a first choice import/export format
                    for IntEnz reactions. In addition it is attractive to use some of
                   the interfaces provided by BioPAX in our reactions java model
                   as they meet some of the requirements we aim at (association
                   of EC numbers to reactions and cross-referencing of reaction
                   participants, for example).
                    </li>
            </ul>

            <p>The NC-IUBMB and ENZYME have strict requirements on how their
                data and therefore their controlled vocabularies are written. It
                is therefore not possible to use an external source as a
                controlled vocabulary as we would be unable to guarantee the
                formatting required by ENYZME and NC-IUBMB. For this reason we
                need to use ChEBI as our controlled vocabulary because
                <ul>
                    <li>it contains all the molecules needed by IntEnz,</li>
                	<li>it is written in the XML format required by IntEnz and
                        hence allows conversion to the other views, i.e. ENZYME
                        and NC-IUBMB, and</li>
                	<li>it decreases redundancy as we will not have to maintain
                        our own controlled vocabulary.</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
           </subsection>
        </section>

        <a name="Potential_external"/>
        <section name="Potential external users of enhanced IntEnz reactions">
            <img src="../../../images/reactionsSpec/reactionsUsers.png"
                 alt="IntEnz reactions users"/>
            <ul>
                <li><a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/embl/index.html">EMBL</a>:
                	the submissions to EMBL database include annotations with
                	EC numbers, which poses the same old problem of having
                	instable public identifiers. In that cases, EMBL could check
                    the EC no in IntEnz and keep a cross-reference to a
                	reaction id.<br/>
                	Another request from EMBL was having some kind of taxonomy
                	information for the reaction. That is out of this
                    specification's scope, but could be achieved by linking
                	to Reactome of GO databases.</li>
                <li><a href="http://www.reactome.org/">Reactome</a>:
                    Bernard de Bono has showed interest in linking to IntEnz
                    reactions, as well as importing them into Reactome be it
                    using web services or an XML interchange format (BioPAX).
                    </li>
                <li><a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro">InterPro</a>:
                    metabolic pathways are described as sequences of InterPro
                    entries, which map to EC numbers. Some of their entries
                    have a <code>reaction</code> XML tag which contains a
                    reaction as plain text. IntEnz reactions could be used by
                    InterPro to link and update such information, in order to
                    display reactions for InterPro entries. To that end, their
                    curators would need to search the IntEnz reactions database.
                    </li>
            </ul>
	    </section>

       <a name="Use-cases"/>
        <section name="Use-cases">
            <subsection name="Abstract reactions">
                <p>An <b>abstract reaction</b> has no clear definition of the
                    biochemical process, the ambiguity coming from a broad range
                    of reactants and/or products. Thus, its participants cannot
                    be easily mapped to ChEBI. The only information for an
                    abstract reaction is a textual description.<br/>
                    This is the way in which every reaction is treated currently
                    in IntEnz.</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Simple reactions">
                <p>A <b>simple reaction</b> has no steps. It can be part of an
                    overall (complex) reaction, i.e. be a <b>step reaction</b>.
                    </p>
                <img src="../../../images/reactionsSpec/reactionsSimpleUcd.png"
                     alt="Use-case diagram"/>
                <p>Deletion of reactions is actually a change of status (the
                    data won't be removed from the database), much in the same
                    way deletion of compounds is handled in ChEBI.</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Complex reactions">
                <p>A <b>complex (overall) reaction</b> has two or more steps
                    (simple reactions).</p>
                <img src="../../../images/reactionsSpec/reactionsComplexUcd.png"
                     alt="Use-case diagram"/>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Cofactors">
                <p>Though not being part of the reaction itsef, <b>cofactors</b>
                    will be reimplemented to take advantage of the new mapping
                    to ChEBI, favouring the reuse of data in IntEnz.</p>
                <img src="../../../images/reactionsSpec/reactionsCofactorsUcd.png"
                     alt="Use-case diagram"/>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Enzyme entries">
                <p>The assignment of reactions - simple or complex ones - to an
                    enzyme entry will allow curators to select from existing
                    reactions in the database, or create new ones if necessary.
                    <br/>
                    Several reactions assigned to the same enzyme entry are
                    considered as alternative reactions. Sorting of alternative
                    reactions will be implemented as well.</p>
                <img src="../../../images/reactionsSpec/reactionsEnzymeUcd.png"
                     alt="Use-case diagram"/>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="IntEnz reactions users">
                <p>End users and curators will query IntEnz for reactions
                    (by EC number, reactant/product ChEBI id, reactant/product
                    name...) using a web interface.<br/>
                    External databases will update cross references to stable
                    public reaction id's, querying the database or - in the
                    future - using webservices.</p>
                <img src="../../../images/reactionsSpec/reactionsUsersUcd.png"
                     alt="Use-case diagram"/>
            </subsection>
        </section>

        <a name="Requirements"/>
        <section name="Requirements">

            <subsection name="Dependencies on existing systems">
                <p>
                    The mapping of reactants, cofactors and products requires
                    the use of the <b>ChEBI</b> database. It can be achieved in
                    several ways:
                    <ol style="list-style: lower-alpha">
                        <li>Acting as a direct client of the ChEBI database,
                            using JDBC for example.</li>
                        <li>Acting as a client of the ChEBI internal Web
                            Services, using HTTP calls.</li>
                    </ol>
                    The second solution seems simpler and cleaner, while
                    providing all the information IntEnz needs about compounds.
                    Drawback: not only the ChEBI database must be available,
                    but the web services too.<br/>
                    The retrieval of data from ChEBI would be only at curation
                    time, to avoid overhead. So any needed compound information
                    would be stored in the IntEnz DB and updated appropriately
                    with every IntEnz release.
               </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Platform requirements">
                <p>
                    IntEnz would need access to ChEBI, by adding the needed
                    <b>web services</b> jar files and configuration files to the
                    distribution.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Data fields required">
                <p>An <b>unbalanced ("abstract") reaction</b> must have just a
                    textual representation, like the current equation field.</p>
                <p>A <b>balanced ("chemical") reaction</b> must meet the
                    following requirements:
                    <ul>
                        <li>Have one or more different <b>reactants</b>.</li>
                        <li>Have one or more different <b>products</b>.</li>
                        <li>No reactant may exist among products, and viceversa.
                            (there are exceptions to this rule!, in which case
                            the reaction could be handled as unbalanced).</li>
                        <li>Reactants and products must map to other database(s)
                            - namely ChEBI - from which data - <b>name</b>,
                            <b>formula</b> ... - will be collected and updated.
                            Besides, they will have a <b>coefficient</b> for
                            stoichiometry purposes.</li>
                        <li>The <b>stoichiometry</b> must be valid.</li>
                        <li>The reaction must be the same independently of
                            the participants names (synonyms) and ordering.
                            (This is independent of the final representation, as
                            some reactions will need some cosmetic reordering,
                            to put water after any other participants, for
                            example).
                            </li>
                        <li>Whenever a reactant/product is shown as an option -
                            "an aldehyde or ketone", for instance - the reaction
                            will split into alternative reactions.</li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>A reaction will have four possible <b>directions</b>:
                	<ul>
                		<li>"Left to right" (reactants -> products)</li>
                		<li>"Right to left" (products -> reactants)</li>
                		<li>Bidirectional</li>
                		<li>Unknown directionality</li>
               		</ul>
               		Each of the directions will have a different unique identifier
               		which will not include any directionality information.<br/>
               		In case it is known that one of the directions does never
               		happen, its status - see below - will be set to
               		<i>obsolete</i> and so will (automatically) bidi/unknown
               		identifiers.</p>
                <p>Reactions will have a <b>status</b> flag to avoid real
                    deletions in the database and hence to enforce stable
                    identifiers.</p>
                <p>Reactions will be <b>unique</b> within the database, that is:
                    one reaction could be assigned to more than one enzyme
                    (reusable).</p>
                <p>Reactions could have <b>comments</b> and<b>links</b> to
                	other databases (KEGG reactions, MACiE).
                    Links (to KEGG "IUBMB" reactions, for example) will be
                    automated whenever possible.</p>
                <p>Reactions will have <b>qualifiers</b>:
                	<i>"Polymerization"</i>, <i>"Class of reactions"</i> and
                	<i>"Chemically balanced"</i>
                	(<i><strike>"Spontaneous"</strike></i> has been discarded).
                	These qualifiers are not mutually exclusive, and should
                	be automated whenever possible, but still letting curators
                	to annotate the reactions.</p>
                <p><b>Complex (overall) reactions</b> will be made of two or
                    more <b>single (step) reactions</b>. Summing single
                    reactions will be possible, to yield a complex one.
                    Splitting a simple reaction into steps will convert it
                    into a complex one.<br/>
                    Validation will be applied to complex reactions as well as
                    their steps. Every step reaction will have a global
                    coefficient in order to balance apropriately the overall
                    reaction.<br/>
                    For now, just one level of complexity will be allowed, that
                    is a complex reaction of this type cannot be part (step)
                    of another complex reaction.</p>
                <p><strike>Step reactions will have a qualifier attached to it
               		which defines it as a "Primary" reaction or "Secondary"
               		reaction.</strike> (this was discarded, as it was really
               		meant to be applied to elementary reactions - see below -,
               		but even these cannot be qualified like this in an
               		absolute way)</p>
                <p>Other type of <b>complex (coupled) reactions</b> will have no
                	specified steps, but will be the sum of two or more
                	simultaneous unordered <b>elementary reactions</b>, which
                	will act as reusable building blocks (for example,
                	hydrolysis of ATP).<br/>
                	These complex reactions without steps could act as steps
                	in an overall transformation.</p>
                <p>Reactions which currently include an <code>OR</code> operator
                    in its equation text ("an aldehyde or ketone", for example)
                    would split into two alternative reactions for the enzyme
                    entry.</p>
                <p>Complex <b>cofactors</b> (text including the operators ";",
                	"and", "or") will be splitand mapped to ChEBI. The
                	<code>OR</code> operator could have several meanings (to be
                	decided if one is enough).</p>
            </subsection>

        </section>

        <a name="Influence"/>
        <section name="Influence on existing systems">
            <subsection name="IntEnz database">
                <p>
                	The <b>database schema</b> should be modified as follows:
                    <ul>
                        <li>The current REACTIONS table will become
                            obsolete, as abstract reactions will also be stored
                            in the new table...</li>
                        <li>A new table
                            <b>INTENZ_REACTIONS</b> as a hub for other
                            tables containing detailed data. It will store
                            essential data as well as columns to speed up
                            reactions search - FINGERPRINT - and visualization
                            - EQUATION.</li>
                        <li>A new table
                            <b>REACTIONS_MAP</b> to map enzyme ids to reaction
                            ids, as well as store the ordering of alternative
                            reactions and web view for complex reactions (should
                            their steps be shown?).</li>
                        <li>A new table
                            <b>COMPLEX_REACTIONS</b> will store a mapping for
                            overall reactions to their steps, as well as their
                            ordering and coefficient (if needed to balance the
                            overall equation).</li>
                        <li>A new table
                            <b>REACTION_LINKS</b> for any cross references to
                            KEGG reactions, UM-BDB...</li>
                        <li>A new table
                            <b>REACTION_CITATIONS</b> for any bibliographic
                            references to the reaction.</li>
                        <li>A new table
                            <b>CV_REACTION_QUALIFIERS</b>.</li>
                        <li>A new table
                            <b>CV_REACTION_ROLES</b> will store the two possible
                            roles in a reaction.</li>
                        <li>A new table
                            <b>REACTION_PARTICIPANTS</b> will link reactions to
                            their reactants and products.</li>
                       <li>A new table
                            <b>CV_REACTION_PARTICIPANT_ROLE</b>.</li>
                        <li>A new table
                            <b>COMPOUND_DATA</b> will store data retrieved from
                            ChEBI.</li>
                        <li>The <b>COFACTORS</b> table will have a new column
                            <b>COMPOUND_ID</b>, which will be primary key
                            instead of COFACTOR_TEXT. It will also have two more
                            columns: OPERATOR and OP_GRP, to handle complex
                            cofactor texts.</li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <img src="../../images/reactionsSpec/reactionsDbSchemaModifications2.png"
                     alt="DB schema modifications"/>
                <p>There is an <a href="reactionsExample.html">example</a>
                    available (outdated, as of 2006-10-31).</p>
                <p>
                    As part of the future <b>data integrity checker</b>:
                    <ul>
                        <li>ChEBI id's used by IntEnz should be available in
                            ChEBI, and should not be child compounds (these
                            will be substituted by their parents in case of
                            merging, during routine <b>automated ChEBI updates
                            </b>). Whenever there is a chenge in ChEBI which
                            propagates to IntEnz, both ChEBI and IntEnz
                            curators should be warned to be aware of possible
                            side effects (on enzyme.dat, for example).
                            </li>
                        <li>the stoichiometry of every reaction should be
                            validated, not only at curation time but also
                            after any ChEBI updates which could break the
                            balance.</li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
        	</subsection>

            <subsection name="IntEnz data model">
            <!--
                <p>A new class <b><code>ReactionParticipant</code></b> is needed
                    for reactants and products. Basically, this class would wrap
                    a ChEBI compound and a stoichiometric coefficient. The
                    <b><code>Compound</code></b> class doesn't need all of the
                    complexity of ChEBI implementation, though a common
                    interface should be used.</p>

                <p>The <b><code>Reaction</code></b> class needs some
                    refactoring:
                    <ul>
                        <li>constructor(s)</li>
                        <li>add fields and accessor methods for the reaction id,
                            reaction participants and links to external
                            databases.</li>
                        <li>add a field to map a reaction to a list of enzyme
                            ids.</li>
                        <li>equals and compare methods: should take into account
                            the reaction participants.</li>
                        <li>implement Commented interface.</li>
                        <li>reaction steps could be summed to yield an overall
                            reaction.</li>
                        <li>generate a <i>fingerprint</i> of the reaction based
                            on its participants and their coefficients. This is
                            needed to quickly check the existence of a reaction
                            in the database before inserting it.</li>
                    </ul>
                </p>

                <p><code>Reaction</code> will have two subclasses:
                    <b><code>OverallReaction</code></b> for complex (overall)
                    reactions and <b><code>StepReaction</code></b> for step
                    reactions. Objects of these classes could be connected using
                    <b><code>ComplexReactionMap</code></b>s.</p>

                <p>In order to assign reactions to enzymes, a new class
                    <b><code>ReactionToEnzyme</code></b> will be implemented
                    following the database schema. The
                    <b><code>EnzymeEntry</code></b> class would be modified
                    accordingly.</p>

                <p>The <b><code>Cofactor</code></b> class will become a wrapper
                    around <code>Compound</code>.</p>
             -->

	            <img src="../../images/reactionsSpec/reactionsDomainCd.png"
                    alt="Class diagram"/>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="IntEnz curator tool">
                <p>The classes <b><code>ReactionDTO</code></b> and
                    <b><code>CofactorDTO</code></b> should be modified according
                    to <code>Reaction</code> and <code>Cofactor</code>.</p>

                <p>A validation for stoichiometry - possibly based on the
                    compounds formulae - should be implemented in the
                    <code>biobabel</code> package and used by the
                    <code>ReactionDTO</code> class.</p>

                <p>A new class <b><code>ChebiHelper</code></b>
                    should provide methods to use it as a ChEBI webservices
                    client, retrieving information on the reaction participants:
                    recommended name, formula, structure (image)...
                    <br/>
                    <img src="../../images/reactionsSpec/reactionsHelperCd.png"
                         alt="Class diagram"/>
                </p>

                <p>A new class <b><code>CompoundMapper</code></b> would be
                    responsible for retrieving compound data from the IntEnz
                    database (data already imported from ChEBI). It should be
                    used by <b><code>EnzymeReactionMapper</code></b> and
                    <b><code>EnzymeCofactorMapper</code></b>.
                    <br/>
                    <img src="../../images/reactionsSpec/reactionsMapperCd.png"
                         alt="Class diagram"/>
                </p>

                <p>The <b>web interface</b> should be extended to create and
                    edit reactions (see a
                    <a href="curatorToolModel/index.html">preliminary model</a>.
                    Instead of a plain text field,
                    buttons will be implemented to add alternative reactions,
                    add steps or edit an existing reaction; a reaction editor
                    will show up, including:
                    <ul>
                        <li>Lists of reactants and products</li>
                        <li>Text fields and buttons to populate the mentioned
                            lists with their content</li>
                        <li>Fields to manage links to other databases: GO,
                            Reactome, KEGG...</li>
                        <li>Fields for comments on the reaction</li>
                    </ul>
                    Every reactant and product used by a curator in a reaction
                    should be already present in ChEBI. In order to check this,
                    the queries to ChEBI could be done at different times:
                    <ol style="list-style: lower-alpha">
                        <li>While the curator is selecting a compound.</li>
                        <li>After the curator has submitted a compound name/id.
                        	</li>
                    </ol>
                    The first option - using AJAX technology - not only helps
                    curators, but also avoids typos and use of compounds which
                    don't exist in ChEBI.
                    <br/>
                    Editing a reaction shared by two or more enzymes should
                    display a warning message to avoid undesired changes.
                </p>

                <p>A post-condition should be added to the edition of new
                    reactions: it must not be already present in IntEnz,
                    otherwise the existing reaction will be used. The check
                    would need a <i>fingerprint</i> of the reaction generated
                    from its participants.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="IntEnz releases">
                <p>Before every IntEnz release, a ChEBI data update should be
                    done (similar to the UniProt links import currently in use)
                    to take into account eventual modifications of compounds
                    (formula, name, mergings...).</p>
            </subsection>

        </section>

       <a name="Conclusions"/>
        <section name="Conclusions">
            <p>
               <ul>
                  <li>Database: The database schema designed above has been viewed and corrected
                     by various database specialists at the EBI. In addition the database has been
                     designed with similar systems in mind such as Reactome. It was not possible
                     to exactly adopt the Reactome database schema as it was far more complex than
                     required by IntEnz. However the essential items such as Inputs and Outputs were
                     adopted.<br/>
                     There were certain constraints imposed on the Reaction schema due to our
                     engagement with the NC-IUBMB data schema. For example, we still need to handle
                     unbalanced reactions which are unlikely to be dealt with by NC-IUBMB in the near future.
                     Also the cloning of enzymes means that we are forced to keep the enzymes and reactions
                     in the same schema.
                  </li><br/>
                  <li>Domain Model: The Java Domain Model will be implemented using interfaces from
                  the BioPAX project. The advantage is that we are standard compliant and because it's
                  just an interface (it could always be easily removed if need be) we are not creating
                  an unnecessary dependency. The decision was taken because the API resembled what we
                  are trying to achieve with our reactions. Unfortunately there is no validation framework
                  implemented in any of the domain models we looked at. SBML is another possible output
                  format but it did not seem suitable to use it inhouse.</li><br/>
                  <li>Curator tool: At this point in time there seems no clear advantage to use
                  the Reactome Curator tool over our existing IntEnz tool. The IntEnz curator tool is a
                   standard based system using the STRUTS web framework, Unit Of Work design pattern, STRUTS
                     validation framework, TILES framework, JSTL tag libraries and STRUTS tag libraries.
                     In addition the extention of this tool to accomodate Reactions would be minimal.
                     Another advantage is that we have spent months ironing out the bugs and preferences
                     that SIB and EBI curators had for the tool. It is now in an acceptable state.
                     Introducing a new tool which would require the same amount of effort and bug fixes
                     could cause major havoc to the colloborative spirit of this project.
                  </li>
               </ul>
                </p>
        </section>

       <a name="Timetable"/>
        <section name="Timetable">
            <p>We estimate the project will take approximately 9 months. We have spent about 2 months
               gathering requirements and writing this specification, hence we estimate in another
               7 months we expect the project to be complete. See below for the project deliverables:
                </p>
           <p>
                      <table width="100%">
          <tr>
            <td>
              <b>Priority</b>
            </td>
            <td>
              <b>Description</b>
            </td>
            <td>
              <b>Developer</b>
            </td>
             <td>
              <b>Estimate</b>
            </td>
          </tr>
           <tr>
            <td>
              <b>1.</b>
            </td>
            <td>
              Reaction database design and modelling.
            </td>
            <td>
              RA and PdM
            </td>
            <td>
               10 d
            </td>
          </tr>
           <tr>
            <td>
              <b>2.</b>
            </td>
            <td>
              Reaction database implementation.
            </td>
            <td>
              RA
            </td>
              <td>20</td>
          </tr>

           <tr>
            <td>
              <b>3.</b>
            </td>
            <td>
              Reaction mapping to ChEBI and ChEBI import.
            </td>
            <td>
              RA
            </td>
              <td>45</td>
          </tr>
           <tr>
            <td>
              <b>4.</b>
            </td>
            <td>
               Reaction validator.
            </td>
            <td>
              RA
            </td>
              <td>20</td>
          </tr>
           <tr>
            <td>
              <b>5.</b>
            </td>
            <td>
               Curator tool implementation of Reaction database.
            </td>
            <td>
              RA
            </td>
              <td>40</td>
          </tr>
           <tr>
            <td>
              <b>6.</b>
            </td>
            <td>
               Public tool implementation of Reaction database.
            </td>
            <td>
              RA
            </td>
              <td>20</td>
          </tr>
              </table>
           </p>
        </section>

    </body>

</document>
