<?xml version="1.0" encoding='iso-8859-1'?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="rafalcan@ebi.ac.uk">Rafael Alcantara</author>
    <title>IntEnz - Data requirements and analysis</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="IntEnz - Data requirements and analysis">
      <p>
<h2>Content</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="#ECNUMBERS">EC numbers</a></li>
<li><a href="#CLASSES">Classes</a></li>
<li><a href="#SUBCLASSES">Subclasses</a></li>
<li><a href="#SUBSUBCLASSES">Subsubclasses</a></li>
<li><a href="#ENZYMES">Enzymes</a></li>
<li><a href="#REACTIONS">Reactions</a></li>
<li><a href="#RECNAMES">Recommended names</a></li>
<li><a href="#SYSNAMES">Systematic names</a></li>
<li><a href="#OTHNAMES">Other names</a></li>
<li><a href="#COMMENTS">Comments</a></li>
<li><a href="#COFACTORS">Cofactors</a></li>
<li><a href="#CASNUMBERS">CAS registry numbers</a></li>
<li><a href="#DATACOMMENTS">Data comments</a></li>
<li><a href="#COPYRIGHT">Copyright issues</a></li>


</ul>

<h2><a name="ECNUMBERS">EC numbers</a></h2>

<p>
Also called code numbers, enzyme numbers, enzyme code, enzyme commission
numbers.
</p>

<h3>Description</h3>

<p>
EC numbers consist of one to four numbers separated by dots '.',
for example '1.18.1.3', '3.1', '3.2.1.99'.
These four parts  are of a hierarchical nature, '1.18.1.3' means
'serial number 3 of subsubclass 1 of subclass 18 of class 1'.
</p>

<ol>
<li>The first number is the number of the <a href="#CLASSES">class</a>.</li>
<li>The second number defines the <a href="#SUBCLASSES">subclass</a> inside the class.</li>
<li>The third number defines the <a href="#SUBSUBCLASSES">subsubclass</a> inside the subclass.</li>
<li>The fourth number is a serial number of the enzyme inside the subsubclass.</li>
</ol>

<p>
All four numbers are positive integers.
</p>

<p>
In the literature, the EC number is always preceded by the letters 'EC' and a space.
The IntEnz database does not store the prefix, but may display it on the web pages.
</p>

<p>
Some non-committee datasources use dashes '-' for empty or unspecified fields,
for example '2.1.-.-'. In SWISS-PROT, this is used whenever the enzyme was not
classified by the committee.
The IntEnz database does not support this spelling.
&lt;kirill&gt;<i>'-' stand for unspecified fields because they refer to a
specific enzyme with yet unassigned EC number; it is also not clear whether the
EC number, if assigned, will start with these class, subclass etc. They do
<b>not</b> refer to whole (sub)subclass of enzymes!
Not only SWISS-PROT uses the '-' but also EMBL. See also comment
below.</i>&lt;/kirill&gt;
</p>

<p>
The EC number is the most widely used entity of the enzyme nomenclature work.
Scientists tend to ignore the
<a href="#RECNAMES">accepted name</a> and the <a href="#SYSNAMES">systematic name</a>,
but seem to love the EC number. Every self respecting database with metabolic
data uses the EC numbers or has at least crossreferences to them.

Therefore it is quite likely that the most used entry point into the IntEnz is via
EC numbers. That is certainly true for hyperlinks from other databases.
However, people have difficulties remembering numbers, so interactive access
is more likely to be started using some search words or by browsing.
</p>


<h3>Source</h3>

<p>
EC numbers are authority of the committee, they are therefore shared without
dispute or conflict between the different user views.</p>

<p>
However, IntEnz curators will suggest new enzymes, which have to be approved
by a committee member or automatically after two months. To implement this
automatic approval, the curators have to suggest the first three parts of
the EC number.
</p>


<h3>Domain</h3>

<p>An EC number consists of a tuple of four positive integers.</p>

<ul>
<li>The first number is the number of the <a href="#CLASSES">class</a>
    and has the domain <a href="#DOMAIN-EC1"><b>ec1</b></a>.</li>

<li>The second number is the number of the <a href="#SUBCLASSES">subclass</a>
    and has the domain <a href="#DOMAIN-EC2"><b>ec2</b></a>.</li>

<li>The third number is the number of the <a href="#SUBSUBCLASSES">subsubclass</a>
    and has the domain <a href="#DOMAIN-EC3"><b>ec3</b></a>.</li>

<li>The forth part is an integer number between 1 and ca 300.
    They start with 1 and increase as needed. It is to be expected that the
    upper bound increases, but certainly not beyond thousands.</li>

<li>All four parts are nullable. To be exact, only trailing nulls are allowed
    by the hierarchical nature. For example, 1.2.null.null is an acceptable
    enzyme number with the meaning class 1, subclass 2, subsubclass and serial
    number not yet decided. However, 1.null.2.3 is not meaningful.
    The distinction between EC 1.2.null.null as for enzyme with
    "not yet assigned" subsubclass and serial number and EC 1.2. as for
    complete identifier for given class+subclass, should be made clear by
    the context that uses the EC number.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Constraints</h3>

<p>Note: The comments in <i>italics</i> are hints about the implementability
and can be safely ignored.</p>

<ul>
<li>EC numbers are unique.
    [<i>unique constraint uq_enzyme$ec_quad</i>]</li>

<li>EC numbers are only assigned by the committee.
    [<i>privileged stored procedure?</i>]</li>

<li>EC numbers are never recycled once they are proposed or accepted
    by IUBMB and publicised to the general public, for instance on
    a web page or servlet.
    On a technical side note, this should be stricly enforced.
    However, we might have to implement an 'unlocking' procedure to
    fix the accidental typo or otherwise mistakenly 'used' EC number.
    [<i>table for used ec numbers, before insert and update trigger checks
    this table and raises application error if found</i>]</li>

<li>The first, second and third number have to be controlled. In other words,
    the database should reject EC numbers which refer to a non-existing class,
    class.subclass, class.subclass.subsubclass tuple.
    [<i>foreign key cascade</i>]</li>
</ul>


<h3>Functions</h3>

<ul>
<li>Find enzyme by complete EC number <i>(many per day)</i>.</li>

<li>Is a.b.c.d a valid approved number <i>(quaterly check by other EBI databases)</i>.</li>

<li>Find all enzymes with an EC number that starts with a.b .</li>

<li>What is the next free (and never used) serial number for a.b.c?</li>

<li>Assign the next free (and never used) serial number for a.b.c to a new enzyme.</li>

<li>Populate database with an approved published enzyme number <i>(initial loading)</i>.</li>

<li>Sort a set of EC numbers numerically.</li>

</ul>



<h2><a name="CLASSES">Classes</a></h2>

<h3>Description</h3>
<p>
This is the highest level of the enzyme hierarchy. There are currently
six different classes, 1 to 6. It is unlikely that there will be more
classes in future.
</p>

<h3>Attributes</h3>
<ul>
<li>EC number of the class, example '3'.
    </li>
<li>Name, example 'Hydrolases'.
    </li>
<li>Description. A short paragraph explaining the contents of the class.
&lt;kirill&gt;<i>Currently, descriptions to classes and subclasses could
be found in "Introduction" files, e.g.
<a href="http://www.chem.qmul.ac.uk/iubmb/enzyme/EC4/intro.html">
http://www.chem.qmul.ac.uk/iubmb/enzyme/EC4/intro.html</a>
</i>&lt;/kirill&gt;

    </li>
<li>Status.
    </li>
</ul>

<p>In the unlikely event of a new class being created, it has to undergo
the approval mechanism, which needs a status flag and a edit history.
As with all hierarchy elements, only the committee can create new
instances, therefore only <tt>PROPOSED</tt>, <tt>REJECTED PROPOSED</tt>
and <tt>APPROVED</tt> are legal states.</p>
&lt;kirill&gt;<i>Indeed it is highly unlikely however I don't see why the new
hierarchy elements can not be SUGGESTED in principle.</i>&lt;/kirill&gt;

<h3>Unique identifier</h3>
<p>Classes are uniquely identified by their EC number. This number is also
the only plausible entry point besides browsing through the classes.</p>

<h3>Source</h3>
<p>Classes are only assigned by the enzyme committee.
The name and description is found on the IUBMB web pages and in the
expasy file ENZCLASS.TXT, the contents should be identical, while the
spelling and encoding might be slightly different.</p>

<h3>Domains</h3>
<ul>
<li>EC number:
    domain <a name="DOMAIN-EC1"><b>ec1</b></a>, positive integer.
    There are currently six different classes, 1 to 6. It is unlikely that
    there will be more numbers in future, certainly never more than ten.
    </li>
<li>Name: String, current maximal length 20 characters.<br/>
    Currently no special characters, but possibly for new classes.
    </li>
<li>Description: String, current maximal length 745 characters,
    on average 470 <![CDATA[ &plusmn;]]> 240.<br/>
    Can contain special characters.
    </li>
<li>Status: domain <b>status</b>, enumeration.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Constraints</h3>

<p>Note: The comments in <i>italics</i> are hints about the implementability
and can be safely ignored.</p>

<ul>
<li>The EC number is unique and mandatory.
    [<i>unique constraint/primary key</i>]</li>
<li>The EC number is a positive integer.
    [<i>check constraint</i>]</li>
<li>EC numbers should never be recycled. However, it is doubtful if this
    has to be enforced, as a new or deleted class is an extremely rare
    and unlikely event, which is closely watched by the community.</li>
<li>The name is mandatory.
    [<i>unique constraint</i>]<br/>
    [<i>not null constraint</i>]</li>
<li>The name doesn't end on a dot, question or exclamation mark.
    Besides, the name doesn't begin or end with white space.
    [<i>check constraint</i>]</li>
<li>The description is mandatory.
    [<i>not null constraint</i>]</li>
<li>The description does end normally on a dot, question or exclamation mark,
    and it doesn't begin or end with white space.
    [<i>check constraint</i>]</li>
<li>Classes are only created, renamed and deleted by the committee.
    [<i>privileged stored procedure?</i>]
&lt;kirill&gt;<i>I don't see why the new classes can not be SUGGESTED in
principle.</i>&lt;/kirill&gt;
</li>
</ul>


<h3>Functions</h3>

<ul>
<li>Find a class by EC number <i>(many per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Is 'a' a valid class number (<i>few per day for referential integrity</i>).</li>
<li>List all classes with number and name <i>(many per day for browsing)</i>.</li>
<li>What is the next free (and never used) class EC number <i>(never, besides, the
    answer can be found out manually.)</i>.</li>
<li>Populate database with classes from IUBMB web pages <i>(initial loading)</i>.</li>
</ul>



<h2><a name="SUBCLASSES">Subclasses</a></h2>

<h3>Description</h3>
<p>
This is the second level of the enzyme hierarchy.
A subclass is always part of a <a href="#CLASSES">class</a>.
For example, the subclass EC 3.1 'Acting on ester bonds' is a child of
the class EC 3 'Hydrolases'.
</p>


<h3>Attributes</h3>
<ul>
<li>EC number of the subclass, example '3.1'.
    </li>
<li>Name, example 'Acting on ester bonds'.
    This name makes only sense inside it's class.
    </li>
<li>Description. A short paragraph explaining the contents of the subclass.

&lt;kirill&gt;<i>Currently, descriptions to classes and subclasses could
be found in "Introduction" files, e.g.
<a href="http://www.chem.qmul.ac.uk/iubmb/enzyme/EC4/intro.html">
http://www.chem.qmul.ac.uk/iubmb/enzyme/EC4/intro.html</a>
</i>&lt;/kirill&gt;
    </li>
<li>Status.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Unique identifier</h3>
<p>Subclasses are uniquely identified by their EC number tuple.</p>

<h3>Source</h3>
<p>Subclasses are only assigned by the enzyme committee.
The name and description is found on the IUBMB web pages and in the
expasy file ENZCLASS.TXT, the contents should be identical, while the
spelling and encoding might be slightly different.</p>

<h3>Domains</h3>
<ul>
<li>EC number:
    The first part of the EC number is of the
    domain <a href="#DOMAIN-EC1"><b>ec1</b></a>.
    The second part of the EC number is of the
    domain <a name="DOMAIN-EC2"><b>ec2</b></a>, an positive integer,
    currently ranging from 1,2,3,...,18,19,97,99.
    There may be higher numbers in future, but unlikely
    more than hundreds.
    </li>
<li>Name: String, current maximal length 177 characters, on average
    36 <![CDATA[ &plusmn;]]> 26 characters.<br/>
    Can contain special characters.
    </li>
<li>Description: String, current maximal length 1950 characters,
    on average 460 <![CDATA[ &plusmn;]]> 440 characters. The description is not unique.<br/>
    Can contain special characters.
    </li>
<li>Status: domain <b>status</b>, enumeration.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Constraints</h3>

<p>Note: The comments in <i>italics</i> are hints about the implementability
and can be safely ignored.</p>

<ul>
<li>The EC number tuple is unique and mandatory.
    [<i>unique constraint/primary key</i>]</li>
<li>The first EC number has to be a valid class number.
    [<i>foreign key</i>]</li>
<li>The second EC number is a positive integer.
    [<i>check constraint</i>]</li>
<li>EC numbers should never be recycled.</li>
<li>The name is mandatory but may be not unique in future.
    [<i>not null constraint</i>]</li>
<li>The name doesn't end on a dot, question or exclamation mark.
    Besides, the name doesn't begin or end with white space.
    [<i>check constraint</i>]</li>
<li>The description is optional and not unique
    (for example EC 4.99 and EC 5.99 'A subclass of miscellaneous enzymes.')
    [<i>null constraint</i>]</li>
<li>The description does end normally on a dot, question or exclamation mark,
    and it doesn't begin or end with white space.
    [<i>check constraint</i>]</li>
<li>Subclasses are only created, renamed and deleted by the committee.
    [<i>privileged stored procedure?</i>]
&lt;kirill&gt;<i>I don't see why the new subclasses can not be
SUGGESTED in principle.</i>&lt;/kirill&gt;
</li>
</ul>


<h3>Functions</h3>

<ul>
<li>Find a subclass by EC number <i>(many per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Is 'a.b' a valid subclass number (<i>few per day for referential integrity</i>).</li>
<li>What is the class number of a given subclass? <i>(many per day for browsing)</i>.</li>
<li>List all subclasses of a given class with number and name <i>(many per day for browsing)</i>.</li>
<li>What is the next free (and never used) subclass EC number. This function has
    to fill the gaps before the magic numbers 97 and 99 <i>(rarely)</i>.</li>
<li>Populate database with subclasses from IUBMB web pages <i>(initial loading)</i>.</li>
<li>Create a new subclass, given the class it belongs to, the new name and optionally
    a description. <i>(rarely)</i>.</li>
<li>Delete an existing subclass. All it's children will have been taken care of before
    the deletion <i>(very rare)</i>.</li>
</ul>





<h2><a name="SUBSUBCLASSES">Subsubclasses</a></h2>

<h3>Description</h3>
<p>
This is the third level of the enzyme hierarchy.
A subsubclass is always part of a <a href="#SUBCLASSES">subclass</a>.
For example, the subsubclass EC 3.1.1 'Carboxylic ester hydrolases' is a child
of subclass EC 3.1 'Acting on ester bonds'.
</p>


<h3>Attributes</h3>
<ul>
<li>EC number of the subsubclass, example '3.1.1'.
    </li>
<li>Name, example 'Carboxylic ester hydrolases'.
    This name makes only sense inside it's subclass.
    </li>
<li>Description. A short paragraph explaining the contents of the subsubclass.
    </li>
<li>Status.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Unique identifier</h3>
<p>Subsubclasses are uniquely identified by their EC number tuple.</p>

<h3>Source</h3>
<p>Subsubclasses are only assigned by the enzyme committee.
The name and description is found on the IUBMB web pages and in the
expasy file ENZCLASS.TXT, the contents should be identical, while the
spelling and encoding might be slightly different.</p>

<h3>Domains</h3>
<ul>
<li>EC number:
    The first part of the EC number is of the
    domain <a href="#DOMAIN-EC1"><b>ec1</b></a>.
    The second part of the EC number is of the
    domain <a href="#DOMAIN-EC2"><b>ec2</b></a>
    The third part of the EC number is of the
    domain <a name="DOMAIN-EC3"><b>ec3</b></a>, an positive integer,
    currently ranging from 1,2,3,...,29,30,99.
    There may be higher numbers in future, but unlikely
    more than hundreds.
    </li>
<li>Name: String, current maximal length 130 characters, on average
    34 <![CDATA[ &plusmn;]]> 24 characters.<br/>
    Can contain special characters.
    </li>
<li>Description: String, current maximal length unknown.
    The description is not unique.<br/>
    Can contain special characters.
    </li>
<li>Status: domain <b>status</b>, enumeration.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Constraints</h3>

<p>Note: The comments in <i>italics</i> are hints about the implementability
and can be safely ignored.</p>

<ul>
<li>The EC number tuple is unique and mandatory.
    [<i>unique constraint/primary key</i>]</li>
<li>The first and second EC number has to be a valid subclass number.
    [<i>foreign key</i>]</li>
<li>The third EC number is a positive integer.
    [<i>check constraint</i>]</li>
<li>EC numbers should never be recycled.</li>
<li>The name is <kirill><b>not mandatory and may be not unique</b></kirill> in future.
    [<i>null constraint</i>]</li>
<li>The name doesn't end on a dot, question or exclamation mark.
    Besides, the name doesn't begin or end with white space.
    [<i>check constraint</i>]</li>
<li>The description is optional and not unique.
    [<i>null constraint</i>]</li>
<li>The description does end normally on a dot, question or exclamation mark,
    and it doesn't begin or end with white space.
    [<i>check constraint</i>]</li>
<li>Subsubclasses are only created, renamed and deleted by the committee.
    [<i>privileged stored procedure?</i>]
    &lt;kirill&gt;<i>I don't see why the new subsubclasses can not be
    SUGGESTED in principle.</i>&lt;/kirill&gt;</li>
</ul>


<h3>Functions</h3>

<ul>
<li>Find a subsubclass by EC number <i>(many per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Is 'a.b.c' a valid subsubclass number (<i>few per day for referential integrity</i>).</li>
<li>What is the subclass number of a given subsubclass? <i>(many per day for browsing)</i>.</li>
<li>List all subsubclasses of a given subclass with number and name <i>(many per day for browsing)</i>.</li>
<li>What is the next free (and never used) subsubclass EC number. This function has
    to fill the gaps before the magic numbers 97 and 99 <i>(rarely)</i>.</li>
<li>Populate database with subsubclasses from IUBMB web pages <i>(initial loading)</i>.</li>
<li>Create a new subsubclass, given the subclass it belongs to, the new name and optionally
    a description. <i>(rarely)</i>.</li>
<li>Transfer an existing subsubclass to another place in the hierarchy. This is rare,
    but has happened (for example EC 3.1.23).
    Because of it's rarity, it can probably by implemented as creation of the new
    subsubclass, transfer of the enzyme, deletion of the old subsubclass with a
    note of what has happened.<i>(very rare)</i>.</li>
<li>Delete an existing subsubclass. All it's children will have been taken care of before
    the deletion <i>(very rare)</i>.</li>
</ul>

<h2><a name="ENZYMES">Enzymes</a></h2>

<p>Also called sometimes entries (in the context of enzyme databases).</p>


<h3>Description</h3>

<p>Enzymes are the main entities of the IntEnz database.</p>


<h3>Attributes</h3>
<ul>
<li>One unique <a href="#ECNUMBERS">EC number</a>,
    for example '3.1.1.1'.</li>
<li>One unique stable accession number.
    This accession number is needed to trace suggested enzymes which don't have
    received an official EC number. It must be stable as it will be used
    by IntEnz curators to track their work, and it might be used by external
    databases like SWISS-PROT.</li>
<li>One mandatory <a href="#RECNAMES">accepted name</a>,
    for example 'carboxylesterase'.</li>
<li>One optional <a href="#SYSNAMES">systematic name</a>,
    for example 'carboxylic-ester hydrolase'.
    It is entered whenever possible, but for some enzymes a full systematic
    name would be pointless and is therefore omitted.</li>
<li>Zero or more  <a href="#OTHNAMES">other names</a>,
    for example 'ali-esterase; B-esterase; monobutyrase'.</li>
<li>One or more <a href="#REACTIONS">reactions</a>,
    for example
    <blockquote><p>
        a carboxylic ester + H<sub>2</sub>O = an alcohol + a carboxylate
    </p></blockquote>

    The cardinality was quite difficult to analyse.
    According to the IUBMB concept, the reaction is defining an enzyme, so one
    would expect it to be a unique mandatory attribute.
    However, Kirill found out that this is not exactly true, or, to be more precise,
    might have to be changed in future.
    <br />

    Some enzymes are not very specific. Rather than targeting a specific
    substrate, it will deal with a whole set of chemically similar substrates.
    Currently, this is modelled in the enzyme list with an English description
    of the set.
    See for example EC 1.1.3.7, which has the reaction
    <blockquote><p>
       an aromatic primary alcohol + O<sub>2</sub> =
       an aromatic aldehyde + H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>
    </p></blockquote>
    and the comment
    <blockquote><p>
       Oxidizes many primary alcohols containing an aromatic ring;
       best substrates are (2-naphthyl)-methanol and 3-methoxybenzyl alcohol
    </p></blockquote>

    Another example would be
    <blockquote><p>
       L-homoserine + NAD(P)<sup>+</sup> = L-aspartate 4-semialdehyde + NAD(P)H
    </p></blockquote>

    which is actually a family of two reactions:
    <blockquote><p>
       L-homoserine + NAD<sup>+</sup> = L-aspartate 4-semialdehyde + NADH<br />
       L-homoserine + NADP<sup>+</sup> = L-aspartate 4-semialdehyde + NADPH
    </p></blockquote>


    An even stronger indicator are comments like 'can also act on substrate X2'.
    See for example EC 1.13.11.44, which has the reaction
    <blockquote><p>
      benzene-1,2,4-triol + O<sub>2</sub> = maleylacetate
    </p></blockquote>
    and the comment
    <blockquote><p>
      6-chlorobenzene-1,2,4-triol (6-chlorohydroxyquinol) is also a
      substrate, yielding 2-chloromaleylacetate
    </p></blockquote>
    Kirill suggested that the latter one should be treated as second(ary) reaction
    or as a member of an reaction family.
    See <a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/~kirill/ec_reactions.txt"
        >www.ebi.ac.uk/~kirill/ec_reactions.txt</a>
    </li>
<li>Zero or more  <a href="#COMMENTS">comments</a>,
    for example 'Wide specificity'.</li>
<li>Zero or more  <a href="#COFACTORS">cofactors</a>,
    for example 'Zinc'.</li>
<li>Zero or more crossreferences to other databases,
    for example 'SWISS-PROT:P14943 (EST2_RABIT)'.</li>
<li>Status.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Unique identifier</h3>
<p>The EC number of an enzyme is unique. Normally, it serves beautifully
as unique identifier. However, this is only true for approved and proposed
enzymes, because suggested enzymes don't have a full EC number.
However, the generic identifier can uniquely identify all enzymes in the database.</p>


<h3>Source</h3>
<p>Data for enzymes are found on the IUBMB web pages and in the
expasy file ENZYME.DAT.
</p>


<h3>Count</h3>

<p>Some notes on the number of enzymes and the expected future:</p>
<table border="1">
<tr> <th>Year</th> <th>Enzymes</th></tr>
<tr> <td>1994</td> <td align="right">3546</td></tr>
<tr> <td>1995</td> <td align="right">3594</td></tr>
<tr> <td>1998</td> <td align="right">3704</td></tr>
<tr> <td>1999</td> <td align="right">3705</td></tr>
<tr> <td>2001</td> <td align="right">3870</td></tr>
</table>

<p>
This is not too impressive (less than 500 for 5 years). Assuming
(unrealistically) 500 new entries next year, 1000 new entries next year,
1500 entries next year etc., we will have increase up to maximum 11,500
entries during the next 5 years.
</p>


<h3>Domains</h3>
<ul>
<li>EC number:
    The four parts of the EC number are of the domains
    <a href="#DOMAIN-EC1"><b>ec1</b></a>,
    <a href="#DOMAIN-EC2"><b>ec2</b></a>,
    <a href="#DOMAIN-EC3"><b>ec3</b></a>,
    <a href="#DOMAIN-EC4"><b>ec4</b></a>, respectively.</li>
<li>Accession number: String.
    </li>
<li>Generic identifier:
    domain <a name="DOMAIN-ENZID"><b>enzid</b></a>.
    Integer.</li>
<li><a href="#RECNAMES">Accepted name</a></li>
<li><a href="#SYSNAMES">Systematic name</a></li>
<li><a href="#OTHNAMES">Other names</a></li>
<li><a href="#REACTIONS">Reactions</a></li>
<li><a href="#COMMENTS">Comments</a></li>
<li><a href="#COFACTORS">Cofactors</a></li>
<li>Crossreferences: List of zero or more crossreferences
   <span class="doublecheck">[To be written]</span></li>
</ul>


<h3>Constraints</h3>

<p>Note: The comments in <i>italics</i> are hints about the implementability
and can be safely ignored.</p>

<ul>
<li>To be completed...
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Functions</h3>

<ul>
<li>To be completed...</li>
</ul>




<h2><a name="REACTIONS">Reactions</a></h2>

<p>Also called catalytic activity.</p>
<p><i>See also the <a href="../../tech_docs/specifications/reactions.html">specification</a> for enhancement
of reacions in IntEnz.</i></p>

<h3>Description</h3>

<p>The enzyme nomenclature system is based on classifying the reactions
that are catalyzed by the enzymes. The reaction is therefore the defining
attribute of an enzyme. </p>

<p>
Normally, the reaction is specified as follows:
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>
substrate<sub>1<sub>1</sub></sub> +
substrate<sub>1<sub>2</sub></sub> [ +
substrate<sub>1<sub><i>n</i></sub></sub>]
=
substrate<sub>2<sub>1</sub></sub> +
substrate<sub>2<sub>2</sub></sub> [ +
substrate<sub>2<sub><i>n</i></sub></sub>]
</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In some cases free text is used to describe a reaction, for example
'Degrades starch to cyclodextrins by formation of a 1,4-alpha-D-glucosidic
bond' and 'Cleaves Leu-|-Leu bond in angiotensinogen to generate angiotensin I'.</p>


<h3>Attributes</h3>
<ul>
<li>Textual representation of the reaction equation, for example
    <blockquote><p>
      L-proline + NAD(P) = 1-pyrroline-2-carboxylate + NAD(P)H
    </p></blockquote>
    </li>
<li>Flag to distinguish chemical equations from free text reactions.
    Not necessarily stored in the database, as an equal sign '='
    is a clear hint for an chemical equation.<br />
    This will become important when we extend the database to
    parse the reaction text using the following operation:
    in all reactions containing ' = ', extract the entities divided by
    ' = ' and ' + ' and tag them as chemicals;
    those on the left of ' = ', are the
    chemicals with role=reactant, those on the right of ' = ' are the
    chemicals with role=product.
    </li>
<li class="doublecheck">Status [do reactions have a status?].
&lt;kirill&gt;<i>Why not -- but then I suggest that every field has the
status (SUGGESTED, PROPOSED and APPROVED) attribute; EC number can only
be PROPOSED or APPROVED.</i>&lt;/kirill&gt;

    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Unique identifier</h3>
<p>Reactions are uniquely identified by their textual representation. This text
is functionally dependent on the EC number.</p>


<h3>Source</h3>
<p>The IUBMB web pages list the reactions in a field 'Reaction:'.
The expasy file ENZYME.DAT lists the reactions in 'CA' line types.
The two sources have different spellings for the special characters,
different conventions (H<sup>+</sup> etc), and have fixed different
errors in their respective versions.
</p>


<h3>Domains</h3>
<ul>
<li>Textual representation: String.
    </li>
<li>Equation/free text flag: boolean or one of EQUATION, FREETEXT.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Constraints</h3>

<p>Note: The comments in <i>italics</i> are hints about the implementability
and can be safely ignored.</p>

<ul>
<li>The reaction text is not necessarily unique.</li>
<li>The reaction text doesn't end on a dot, question or exclamation mark.
    Besides, the name doesn't begin or end with white space.
    [<i>check constraint</i>]</li>
<li>Reactions can be suggested by IntEnz curators, and are proposed and approved
    by enzyme committee members.
    [<i>privileged stored procedure?</i>]</li>
<li>Small typographical errors can be corrected without approval.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Functions</h3>

<ul>
<li>Find a reaction by EC number <i>(many per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Find a reaction that contains a certain substrate (<i>many per day</i>).</li>
<li>Create, update, delete a reaction (<i>few per day</i>).</li>
<li>Populate database with reactions from IUBMB web pages <i>(initial loading)</i>.</li>
<li>Populate database with reactions from ENZYME.DAT file <i>(initial loading)</i>.</li>
<li>Compare IUBMB and ENZYME.DAT version of a reaction <i>(initial merging)</i>.</li>
<li>Suggest change of a reaction <i>(few per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Propose a suggested change <i>(few per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Approve a proposed change <i>(few per day)</i>.<br/>
    <span class="doublecheck">
    [It is unclear if the approval of a reaction can be tied to the approval of
    the full enzyme entry.]</span>
    </li>
<li><i>Optional function for a later stage of the project:</i><br/>
    Check mass and charge balance of an equation. <i>(few per day)</i></li>
<li><i>Optional function for a later stage of the project:</i><br/>
    Retrieve reaction text in SWISS-PROT comment line format
    (<tt>CC -!- CATALYTIC ACTIVITY:</tt>) for insertion into
    TrEMBL entries during automatic annotation <i>(quarterly updates of TrEMBL)</i>.</li>
</ul>




<h2><a name="RECNAMES">Accepted names</a></h2>

<p>Also called description, official name, common name, recommended name.</p>


<h3>Description</h3>
<p>
The recomended name is sufficiently short for general use, but not necessarily
very systematic. In a great many cases it is a name already in current use.
Accepted names for new enzymes are frequently formed as a condensed
version of the systematic name.</p>


<h3>Attributes</h3>

<p>The accepted name is an attribute of an enzyme and has no attributes itself.</p>

<h3>Unique identifier</h3>
<p>Accepted names are identified by their textual representation.
This text is functionally dependent on the EC number.</p>

<h3>Source</h3>
<p>The IUBMB web pages list the accepted name in a field 'Common name:'.
The expasy file ENZYME.DAT lists it in 'DE' line types.
The two sources have different spellings for the special characters,
different conventions (H<sup>+</sup> etc), and have fixed different
errors in their respective versions.
</p>
<p><i>Note:</i> ENZYME.DAT writes accepted names with an initial capital,
for example 'Leucyl aminopeptidase.' compared to the IUBMB version
'leucyl aminopeptidase'.
</p>


<h3>Domains</h3>
<ul>
<li>Textual representation: String.<br />
    Can contain special characters.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Constraints</h3>

<p>Note: The comments in <i>italics</i> are hints about the implementability
and can be safely ignored.</p>

<ul>
<li><b>Sinead:</b> The recommended name is unique (it may occur as an 'other name'
    for some other enzyme but it should be unique for the common-name field.
    Similarly, the systematic name is occasionally used as the common name
    for the same enzyme, but no two systematic names should be the same.
    (In the past we have occassionally given two enzymes the same common name,
    but once we were aware of the error, we changed one of the names).
    [<i>unique constraint</i>]</li>
<li>The accepted name doesn't end on a dot, question or exclamation mark.
    Besides, the name doesn't begin or end with white space.
    [<i>check constraint</i>]</li>
<li>Accepted names can be suggested by IntEnz curators, and are proposed and approved
    by enzyme committee members.
    [<i>privileged stored procedure?</i>]</li>
<li>Small typographical errors can be corrected without approval.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Functions</h3>

<ul>
<li>Find an accepted name by EC number <i>(many per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Find an accepted name that contains a certain phrase (<i>many per day</i>).</li>
<li>Create, update, delete an accepted name (<i>few per day</i>).</li>
<li>Populate database with accepted names from IUBMB web pages <i>(initial loading)</i>.</li>
<li>Populate database with accepted names from ENZYME.DAT file <i>(initial loading)</i>.</li>
<li>Compare IUBMB and ENZYME.DAT version of an accepted name <i>(initial merging)</i>.</li>
<li>Suggest change of an accepted name <i>(few per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Propose a suggested change <i>(few per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Approve a proposed change <i>(few per day)</i>.<br/>
    <span class="doublecheck">
    [It is unclear if the approval of an accepted name can be tied to the approval of
    the full enzyme entry.]</span></li>
<li><i>Optional function:</i><br/>
    Promote an 'other name' to the accepted name<i>(few per day)</i>.</li>
<li><i>Optional function for a later stage of the project:</i><br/>
    Retrieve reaction text in SWISS-PROT description line format
    for insertion into TrEMBL entries during automatic annotation
    <i>(quarterly updates of TrEMBL)</i>.</li>
</ul>




<h2><a name="SYSNAMES">Systematic names</a></h2>


<h3>Description</h3>
<p>
The systematic name of an enzyme is the basis for classification, formed
in accordance with definite rules, shows the action of an enzyme as exactly
as possible, thus identifying the enzyme precisely.</p>


<h3>Attributes</h3>

<p>The systematic name is an attribute of an enzyme and has no attributes itself.</p>

<h3>Unique identifier</h3>
<p>Systematic names are uniquely identified by their textual representation.
This text is functionally dependent on the EC number.</p>

<h3>Source</h3>
<p>The IUBMB web pages list the systematic name in a field 'Systematic name:'.
The expasy file ENZYME.DAT does not contain systematic names.</p>


<h3>Domains</h3>
<ul>
<li>Textual representation: String.<br />
    Can contain special characters.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Constraints</h3>

<p>Note: The comments in <i>italics</i> are hints about the implementability
and can be safely ignored.</p>

<ul>
<li>The systematic name is not necessarily unique in the current dataset,
    but it should be made unique.
    <b>Sinead:</b> The systematic name is occasionally used as the common
    name for the same enzyme, but no two systematic names should be the same.
    [<i>unique constraint</i>]</li>
<li>The systematic name doesn't end on a dot, question or exclamation mark.
    Besides, the name doesn't begin or end with white space.
    </li>
<li>Systematic names can be suggested by IntEnz curators, and are proposed and approved
    by enzyme committee members.
    [<i>privileged stored procedure?</i>]</li>
<li>Small typographical errors can be corrected without approval.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Functions</h3>

<ul>
<li>Find a systematic name by EC number <i>(many per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Find a systematic name that contains a certain phrase (<i>many per day</i>).</li>
<li>Create, update, delete a systematic name (<i>few per day</i>).</li>
<li>Populate database with systematic names from IUBMB web pages <i>(initial loading)</i>.</li>
<li>Suggest change of a systematic name <i>(few per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Propose a suggested change <i>(few per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Approve a proposed change <i>(few per day)</i>.<br/>
    <span class="doublecheck">
    [It is unclear if the approval of a systematic name can be tied to the approval of
    the full enzyme entry.]</span></li>
</ul>




<h2><a name="OTHNAMES">Other names</a></h2>

<p>Also called alternate names, alternative names, synonyms.</p>

<h3>Description</h3>
<p>
To enable the database to be used for finding recommended names, as many
as possible 'other names' that have been used have been included, but are not
recommended. Some of these may only have been used to a small extent.</p>


<h3>Attributes</h3>
<ul>
<li>Name.
    </li>
<li>Order in list. It's was decided not to store the order
    in the database, but generate it on the fly, for instance
    alphabetically or by date of creation.
    </li>
<li>Obsolete flag
    <span class="doublecheck">
    [The book says on p23 that some other names are so obsolete
    that they are flagged 'Obs'. It this true for the web pages?] Kirill didn't
    see it on web pages.
    </span>
    </li>
<li>Misleading flag
    <span class="doublecheck">
    [The book says on p23 that some other names are misleading
    and are flagged 'Mis'. It this true for the web pages?] Kirill: It's not true
    for web pages.
    </span>
    </li>
<li>Status
    <span class="doublecheck">
    [do reactions have a status?]. &lt;kirill&gt;
    <i>Why not -- but then I suggest that every field has the status (SUGGESTED,
    PROPOSED and APPROVED) attribute; EC number can only be PROPOSED or APPROVED.
    </i>&lt;/kirill&gt;
    </span>
    </li>
</ul>

<h3>Unique identifier</h3>
<p>Other names do not have a natural unique identifier.</p>

<h3>Source</h3>
<p>The IUBMB web pages list the other names in a field 'Other names:'.
The expasy file ENZYME.DAT lists it in 'AN' lines.
The two sources have different spellings for the special characters,
different conventions (H<sup>+</sup> etc), and have fixed different
errors in their respective versions.</p>
<p><i>Note:</i> ENZYME.DAT writes other names with an initial capital.
</p>


<h3>Domains</h3>
<ul>
<li>Textual representation: String.<br />
    Can contain special characters.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Constraints</h3>

<p>Note: The comments in <i>italics</i> are hints about the implementability
and can be safely ignored.</p>

<ul>
<li>The other name is not unique.</li>
<li>The other name doesn't end on a dot, question or exclamation mark.
    Besides, the name doesn't begin or end with white space.
    [<i>check constraint</i>]</li>
<li>A list of other names for one enzyme must not contain duplicates.</li>
<li>Other names can be suggested by IntEnz curators, and are proposed and approved
    by enzyme committee members.
    [<i>privileged stored procedure?</i>]</li>
<li>Small typographical errors can be corrected without approval.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Functions</h3>

<ul>
<li>Find a list of other names by EC number <i>(many per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Find an other name that contains a certain phrase (<i>many per day</i>).</li>
<li>Create, update, delete an other name (<i>few per day</i>).</li>
<li>Populate database with other names from IUBMB web pages <i>(initial loading)</i>.</li>
<li>Populate database with other names from ENZYME.DAT file <i>(initial loading)</i>.</li>
<li>Compare IUBMB and ENZYME.DAT version of a list of other names <i>(initial merging)</i>.</li>
<li>Suggest change of an other name <i>(few per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Propose a suggested change <i>(few per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Approve a proposed change <i>(few per day)</i>.<br/>
    <span class="doublecheck">
    [It is unclear if the approval of an other name can be tied to the approval of
    the full enzyme entry.] Astrid: At the beginning IUBMB/Sinead will only be able
    to propose/approve a whole entry. Later on IUBMB/Sinead will be able to propose/approve
    single fields on its ow within an entry like other_names.
    </span></li>
</ul>




<h2><a name="COMMENTS">Comments</a></h2>

<h3>Description</h3>
<p>
Comments are free text notes on an enzyme, and may be used to convey
any useful information.</p>

<p>Some comments show some structure, for example</p>
<ul>
<li>Requires X</li>
<li>Also acts on X</li>
<li>An X protein</li>
<li>Not identical with EC x.x.x.x</li>
</ul>


<h3>Attributes</h3>
<ul>
<li>Comment text.
    </li>
<li>Order in list.
    <span class="doublecheck">
    [Other names come normally as a list of size zero to many.
    We need to decide if we treat it as ordered list or get the order on the fly.]
    </span>
    </li>
<li>Status
    <span class="doublecheck">[do comments have a status?]. &lt;kirill&gt;
    <i>Why not -- but then I suggest that every field has the status (SUGGESTED,
    PROPOSED and APPROVED) attribute; EC number can only be PROPOSED or APPROVED.
    </i>&lt;/kirill&gt; </span>
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Unique identifier</h3>
<p>Comments do not have a natural unique identifier.</p>


<h3>Source</h3>
<p>The IUBMB web pages list the comments in a field 'Comments:'.
This field is free text with one or more sentences.
The expasy file ENZYME.DAT lists comments in 'CC' lines, separating
sentences into multiple comment fields. Furthermore, it lists
cofactor comments in 'CF' lines.
</p>


<h3>Domains</h3>
<ul>
<li>Textual representation: String.<br />
    Can contain special characters.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Constraints</h3>

<p>Note: The comments in <i>italics</i> are hints about the implementability
and can be safely ignored.</p>

<ul>
<li>The comment is not unique.</li>
<li>The comment ends on a dot (i.e. full stop).
    Besides, the comment doesn't begin or end with white space.
    [<i>check constraint</i>]</li>
<li>A list of comments for one enzyme must not contain duplicates.</li>
<li>Comments can be suggested by IntEnz curators, and are proposed and approved
    by enzyme committee members.
    [<i>privileged stored procedure?</i>]</li>
<li>Small typographical errors can be corrected without approval.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Functions</h3>

<ul>
<li>Find a list of other names by EC number <i>(many per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Find an other name that contains a certain phrase (<i>many per day</i>).</li>
<li>Create, update, delete an other name (<i>few per day</i>).</li>
<li>Populate database with other names from IUBMB web pages <i>(initial loading)</i>.</li>
<li>Populate database with other names from ENZYME.DAT file <i>(initial loading)</i>.</li>
<li>Compare IUBMB and ENZYME.DAT version of a list of other names <i>(initial merging)</i>.</li>
<li>Suggest change of an other name <i>(few per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Propose a suggested change <i>(few per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Approve a proposed change <i>(few per day)</i>.<br/>
    <span class="doublecheck">
    [It is unclear if the approval of an other name can be tied to the approval of
    the full enzyme entry.]</span></li>
</ul>



<h2><a name="COFACTORS">Cofactors</a></h2>


<h3>Description</h3>

<p>Cofactors are small molecules required by an enzyme to function properly.</p>

<p>Some enzymes work with a multitude of different cofactors, they are listed
as '<i>a</i> or <i>b</i>'.</p>

<p><i>Note that ChEBI mapping of chemical compounds in IntEnz will change this specification:
cofactors will be identified by unique IDs; multiple cofactors in the same text will be
splitted, and the new implementation will take care of <code>OR</code>/<code>AND</code>
operators.</i></p>

<h3>Attributes</h3>
<ul>
<li>Cofactor name.
    </li>
<li>Order in list.
    <span class="doublecheck">
    [Cofactors come normally as a list of size zero to many.
    We need to decide if we treat it as ordered list or get the order on the fly.]
    </span>
    </li>
<li>Status <span class="doublecheck">[do cofactors have a status ???]. &lt;kirill&gt;
    <i>Why not -- but then I suggest that every field has the status (SUGGESTED,
    PROPOSED and APPROVED) attribute; EC number can only be PROPOSED or APPROVED.
    </i>&lt;/kirill&gt;</span>
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Unique identifier</h3>
<p>Cofactors do not have a natural unique identifier.</p>


<h3>Source</h3>
<p>The IUBMB web pages list the cofactors amongst other information in the
field 'Comments:'. This field is free text with one or more sentences.
The expasy file ENZYME.DAT lists cofactors in 'CF' lines, separating
different cofactors by a semicolon ';'.</p>


<h3>Domains</h3>
<ul>
<li>Textual representation: String.<br />
    Can contain special characters.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Constraints</h3>

<p>Note: The comments in <i>italics</i> are hints about the implementability
and can be safely ignored.</p>

<ul>
<li>The cofactor name is not unique.</li>
<li>The cofactor name doesn't end on a dot, question or exclamation mark.
    Besides, it doesn't begin or end with white space.
    [<i>check constraint</i>]</li>
<li>A list of cofactors for one enzyme must not contain duplicates.</li>
<li>Cofactors can be suggested by IntEnz curators, and are proposed and approved
    by enzyme committee members.
    [<i>privileged stored procedure?</i>]</li>
<li>Small typographical errors can be corrected without approval.
    </li>
</ul>


<h3>Functions</h3>

<ul>
<li>Find a list of cofactors by EC number <i>(many per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Find an cofactor that contains a certain phrase (<i>many per day</i>).</li>
<li>Find enzymes that require a certain confactor (<i>many per day</i>).</li>
<li>Create, update, delete an cofactor (<i>few per day</i>).</li>
<li class="doublecheck">Populate database with other cofactors from IUBMB web pages<i>(initial loading)</i>.</li>
<li>Populate database with other cofactors from ENZYME.DAT file <i>(initial loading)</i>.</li>
<li class="doublecheck">Compare IUBMB and ENZYME.DAT version of a list of other names<i>(initial merging)</i>.</li>
<li>Suggest change of an cofactor <i>(few per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Propose a suggested change <i>(few per day)</i>.</li>
<li>Approve a proposed change <i>(few per day)</i>.<br/>
    <span class="doublecheck">
    [???It is unclear if the approval of an other name can be tied to the approval of
    the full enzyme entry.]  Astrid: At the beginning IUBMB/Sinead will only be able
    to propose/approve a whole entry. Later on IUBMB/Sinead will be able to propose/approve
    single fields on its ow within an entry like cofactors.</span></li>
<li><i>Optional function for a later stage of the project:</i><br/>
    Retrieve cofactor names in SWISS-PROT comment line format
    (<tt>CC -!- COFACTOR:</tt>) for insertion into
    TrEMBL entries during automatic annotation <i>(quarterly updates of TrEMBL)</i>.</li>
</ul>


<h2><a name="CASNUMBERS">CAS registry numbers</a></h2>

<p>Also called CAS numbers, CAS, CASRN.</p>


<h3>Description</h3>

<p>CAS is the abbreviation of <i>Chemical Abstracts</i>, which is a division of the
American Chemical Society. CAS has a registry for chemical substances,
which contains more than 32,000,000 substance records, covering scientific
literature from 1957 to the present. Each substrace is identified by a
unique numeric identifier called a CAS Registry Number.</p>

<p>The CAS registry numbers are universally accepted in nearly all involved
databases. They target not directly enzymes, but rather all chemical substances,
including the substrates found in the reaction.
They are therefore ideally suited for the biochemistry nomenclature
component of BioBabel.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, the registry is a commercial database, and the EBI has no license
for it. The Trinity College group has some informal connections with CAS.
<a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Information/Staff/gill.html">Gill Fraser</a> worked
for CAS and might have some contacts.</p>


<p>Example: <b>58-08-2</b> is the CAS Registry Number for caffeine.</p>

<p>More information can be found on the
<a href="http://www.cas.org">CAS website</a>, especially in the document
<a href="http://www.cas.org/EO/regsys.html">regsys.html</a>
[<a href="mirror-regsys.html">local copy</a>].</p>


<h3>Domain</h3>

<p>A CAS Registry Number includes up to 9 digits which are separated
into 3 groups by hyphens. The first part of the number, starting from
the left, has up to 6 digits; the second part has 2 digits. The final
part consists of a single check digit.</p>

<p>The check digit and it's algorithm is described on the CAS webside
in the document
<a href="http://www.cas.org/EO/checkdig.html">checkdig.html</a>
[<a href="mirror-checkdig.html">local copy</a>].

Some less geeky explanation on the topic can be found at
<a href="http://chemfinder.cambridgesoft.com/errorsfound.asp">ChemFinder</a>
[<a href="mirror-errorsfound.html">local copy</a>].</p>

<p>The Perl-style regular expression is
<code>/[0-9]{1,6}-[0-9]{2}-[0-9]/</code>.</p>

<h3>Source</h3>

<p>The HTML pages have CAS registry numbers for some of the enzymes
in the field 'Links to other databases'.</p>
<p>Furthermore, CAS registry numbers are used by the databases
Medline and LIGAND, but surely without guarantee of correctness.</p>


<h3>Functions</h3>

<ul>
<li>Find an enzyme by it's CAS registry number <i>(many per day)</i>.
    </li>
<li>Create, update, delete the CAS registry number of an enzyme (<i>few per day</i>).
    </li>
<li>Populate database with CAS registry numbers from IUBMB web pages<i>(initial loading)</i>.
    </li>
<li><i>Optional function for a later stage of the project:</i><br/>
    Create, update, delete the CAS registry number of a substrate (<i>few per day</i>).
    </li>
<li><i>Optional function for a later stage of the project:</i><br/>
    Find a substrate by it's CAS registry number and display a list of enzymes
    that use this substrate. <i>(many per day)</i>
    </li>
</ul>


<h2><a name="DATACOMMENTS">Data comments</a></h2>

<h3>Description</h3>
<p>Some data need some extra info. For instance, some CAS numbers have had some text included in the
CAS number field which avoided the proper validation of it. Thus, that extra info should be independent
from - though related to - the data item.</p>

<h3>Attributes</h3>
<ul>
    <li>Comment text</li>
    <li>Comment id: the unique identifier of the comment.</li>
    <li>Enzyme id: the unique identifier of the enzyme this comment applies to.</li>
</ul>
<p>As the comment applies actually to a data item, every data item capable of holding a comment should
have an attribute <code>comment id</code>.</p>

<h3>Unique identifier</h3>
<p>Data comments are uniquely identified by their id (and the enzyme id they apply to, in case of
cloned enzymes).</p>

<h3>Source</h3>
<p>?</p>

<h3>Domain</h3>
<ul>
    <li>Textual representation: String.<br/>May contain special characters.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Constraints</h3>
<ul>
    <li>A data item can hold just one comment.</li>
    <li>The comment text is not unique.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Functions</h3>
<ul>
    <li>Create, update, delete a comment on a data item (<i>few per day</i>).</li>
    <li>Find enzymes with matching data comments (<i>many per day</i>).</li>
</ul>


<h2><a name="COPYRIGHT">Copyright issues</a></h2>

<p>InterPro is asked frequently the copyright question. I found the
following passage in the Enzyme Book:</p>
<blockquote>
The entries are (c) Copyright to the International Union of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, 2000.
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
Enzyme entries, including EC numbers, may be quoted in any publication without permission. The copyright of the enzyme list rests with the IUBMB.
</blockquote>
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
