<?xml version="1.0" encoding='iso-8859-1'?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="wfl@ebi.ac.uk">Wolfgang Fleischmann</author>
    <title>The goal and purpose of the IntEnz database</title>
  </properties>

<!--
  Project: IntEnz
  
  Purpose: Document describing the goal and purpose of the IntEnz database.
  
  Usage:   To be read and double checked by IntEnz group,
           Input for designers.
           
  $Id: goal.xml,v 1.1 2008/01/28 10:58:47 rafalcan Exp $
-->

<body>
    <section name="The goal and purpose of the IntEnz database">

written by Wolfgang Fleischmann

<pre>
  Project: IntEnz
  
  Purpose: Document describing the goal and purpose of the IntEnz database.
  
  Usage:   To be read and double checked by IntEnz group,
           Input for designers.
           
  written by Wolfgang Fleischmann 26.01.2002 17:48:14


***************************************************************************

GOAL AND PURPOSE OF THE IntEnz DATABASE

The goal: To construct a consistent database of enzyme nomenclature. 

To (be able to): 

   1. Organise the enzyme knowledge in a systematic, non-redundant way. 
   2. For new enzymes: provide efficient data flow from conception 
      (annotator's suggestion) to birth (officially endorsed entries). 
   3. Provide controlled vocabulary of terms relevant to enzymatic activity. 
   4. Make it easy to crosslink the entries to other biological databases 
      (such as: SPTR, EMBL, InterPro, GO, PDB etc.) via different fields. 

****************************************************************************

ASTRID: Definitions IUBMB Data - DATA REQUIREMENTS AND ANALYSIS 

NC-IUBMB provides data within the following data fields:

NUMBER
Each from IUBMB classified enzyme has an accession number (e.g. 1.2.3.4).
Some enzyme are not classified from IUBMB yet.
When citing an enzyme number from the list, it should be preceded by EC and 
a space.

CLASSIFICATION
The first Enzyme Commission devised a system for classification of enzymes 
that also serves as a basis for assigning code numbers to them. These code 
numbers are prefixed by EC and contain four elements seperated by points.

(i)	the first number shows to which of the six main devisions (classes) 
	the enzyme belongs,
(ii)	the second figure indicates the subclass,
(iii)	the third figure gives the sub-subclass,
(iv)	the fourth figure is the serial number of the enzyme in its 
	sub-subclass.

REACTION
Each classified enzyme has one reaction. 

RECOMMENDED NAME
The recomended name is sufficiently short for general use, but not necessarily 
very systematic. In a great many cases it is a name already in current use.
Recommended names for new enzymes are frequently formed as a condensed 
version of the systematic name.

OTHER NAME(S) (&#62;=0 per entry)


SYSTEMATIC NAME (&#60;=1)
The systematic name of an enzyme is the basis for classification, formed 
in accordance with definite rules, shows the action of an enzyme as exactly 
as possible, thus identifying the enzyme precisely.

COMMENTS (&#62;=0 per entry)


REFERENCES (&#62;=1)

*****************************************************************************

ASTRID: Definitions ENZYME Data - DATA REQUIREMENTS AND ANALYSIS
Amos Bairoch calls it "ENZYME - Enzyme nomenclature database".

The 'ENZYME' data bank contains the following data for each type of
characterized enzyme for which an EC number has been provided:

 ID  -  EC number
 DE  -  Recommended name
 AN  -  Alternative names (if any)
 CA  -  Catalytic activity
 CF  -  Cofactors (if any)
 DR  -  Pointers to  the SWISS-PROT  entrie(s) that  correspond to the enzyme
        (if any)
 DI  -  Pointers to disease(s) associated with a deficiency of the enzyme (if
        any)

The currently used line types, along with their respective line codes, are listed 
below:

   ID  Identification                         (Begins each entry; 1 per entry)
   DE  Description (official name)            (&#62;=1 per entry)
   AN  Alternate name(s)                      (&#62;=0 per entry)
   CA  Catalytic activity                     (&#62;=0 per entry)
   CF  Cofactor(s)                            (&#62;=0 per entry)
   CC  Comments                               (&#62;=0 per entry)
   DI  Disease(s) associated with the enzyme  (&#62;=0 per entry)
   PR  Cross-references to PROSITE            (&#62;=0 per entry)
   DR  Cross-references to SWISS-PROT         (&#62;=0 per entry)
   //  Termination line                       (Ends each entry; 1 per entry)

Some entries do not contain all of the line types, and some line types occur 
many times in a single entry. Each entry must begin with an identification 
line (ID) and end with a terminator line (//).

THE DIFFERENT LINE TYPES
This section describes in detail the format of each type of line used in
the database.

1.  ID line
The ID  (IDentification) line is always the first line of an entry. The format 
of the ID line is:

    ID   EC NUMBER

    Examples:

    ID   1.1.1.1
    ID   6.3.2.1

2.  DE line
The DE  (DEscription) line(s) contain the NC-IUB recommended name for an enzyme. 
The format of the DE line is:

    DE   DESCRIPTION.

    Examples:

    DE   Alcohol dehydrogenase.

    DE   UDP-N-acetylmuramoylalanyl-D-glutamyl-2,6-diaminopimelate--D-
    DE   alanyl-D-alanyl ligase.

    Important note: enzymes are  sometimes deleted from the EC list, others
    are renumbered; however the  NC-IUBMB does not allocate the old numbers
    to new enzymes. Obsolete EC numbers are indicated in this data bank by
    the following DE line syntaxes. For deleted enzymes:

    DE   Deleted entry.

    and for renumbered enzymes:

    DE   Transferred entry: x.x.x.x.

    where x.x.x.x  is the new, valid, EC number; as shown in the following
    example:

    DE   Transferred entry: 1.7.99.5.

3.  AN line
The AN (Alternate Name) line(s) are used to indicate the different name(s), 
other than the NC-IUBMB recommended name, that are used in the literature 
to describe an enzyme. The format of the AN line is:

    AN   NAME.

    As an example we list here both the DE and AN lines for the enzyme EC
    2.7.7.31:

    DE   DNA nucleotidylexotransferase.
    AN   Terminal addition enzyme.
    AN   Terminal transferase.
    AN   Terminal deoxyribonucleotidyltransferase.

4.  CA line
The CA (Catalytic Activity) line(s) are used to indicate the reaction(s)
catalyzed by an enzyme. The format of the CA line is:

    CA   REACTION.

    Where the reaction is indicated following the recommendations of the NC-
    IUBMB. The majority of the reactions are described using a standard chemical 
    reaction format:

    CA   SUBSTRATE_11 + SUBSTRATE_12 [+ SUBSTRATE_1N...]  = SUBSTRATE_21 +
    CA   SUBSTRATE_22 [+ SUBSTRATE_2N].

    As shown in the following examples:

    CA   L-malate + NAD(+) = oxaloacetate + NADH.

    CA   2 ATP + L-glutamine + CO(2) + H(2)O = 2 ADP + phosphate +
    CA   glutamate + carbamoyl phosphate.

    In some cases free text is used to describe a reaction. As shown in the
    following examples:

    CA   Degrades starch to cyclodextrins by formation of a 1,4-alpha-D-
    CA   glucosidic bond.

    CA   Cleaves Leu-|-Leu bond in angiotensinogen to generate
    CA   angiotensin I.


    Notes

    -  Subscript and superscript are indicated between brackets: for example
       NAD+ and NADP+ are indicated as NAD(+) and NADP(+), H2O as H(2)O, CO2
       as CO(2), etc.
    -  Greek letters are spelled out.

5.  CF line
The CF (CoFactor) line(s) are used to indicate which cofactor(s) are
required by an enzyme. The format of the CF line is:

    CF   COFACTOR_1; COFACTOR_2 OR COFACTOR_3[; COFACTOR_N...].

    Examples:

    CF   Pyridoxal-phosphate.
    CF   Molybdenum or vanadium; Iron-sulfur.
    CF   Iron; Ascorbate.

6.  CC line
The CC lines are free text comments on the entry, and may be used to convey 
any useful information.

    Examples:

    CC   -!- The product spontaneously isomerizes to L-ascorbate.

    CC   -!- Some members of this group oxidize only primary alcohols;
    CC       Others act also on secondary alcohols.

7.  DI line
The DI  (DIsease) line(s)  are used  to indicate  the  known  disases(s)
associated with  a deficiency  of the enzyme. Currently this information
is only given for human diseases listed in the MIM database [2].

    [2]  Pearson  P., Francomano C., Foster P., Bocchini C., Li P.,
        McKusick V.A.
        Nucleic Acids Res. 22:3470-3473(1994).

    The format of the DI line is:

    DI   DISEASE_NAME; MIM:NUMBER.

    Where 'NUMBER' is the MIM catalog number of the disease (or phenotype).

    Examples:

    DI   Xanthinuria; MIM:278300.
    DI   Phenylketonuria; MIM:261600.

8.  PR line
The PR (Prosite Reference) line(s) are used as pointers to the PROSITE
document entries that mentions the enzyme being described. The format of
the PR line is:

    PR   PROSITE; PSITE_DOC_AC_NB

    where 'PSITE_DOC_AC_NB' is a PROSITE document entry accession number.
    Example:

    PR   PROSITE; PDOC00065;

9.  DR line
The DR (Data bank Reference) line(s) are used as pointers to the SWISS-
PROT entries that corresponds to the enzyme being described. The format 
of the DR line is:

    DR   AC_NB, ENTRY_NAME;  AC_NB, ENTRY_NAME;  AC_NB, ENTRY_NAME;

    where:

    -  'AC_NB' is  the SWISS-PROT  primary accession  number of the entry to
       which reference is being made.
    -  'ENTRY_NAME' is the SWISS-PROT entry name.

    Example:

    DR   P00366, DHE3_BOVIN;  P00368, DHE3_CHICK;  P00367, DHE3_HUMAN;
    DR   P10860, DHE3_RAT  ;

10. // line 
The // (terminator) line contains no data or comments. It designates the end 
of an entry.

*************************************************************************

WOLFGANG: 

Enzyme

The main entity of the IntEnz database is an enzyme.

Properties:
Most enzymes have an unique -&#62;EC number. 
All enzymes belong to a subsubclass. The -&#62;subsubclass is specified by the 
first three parts of the EC number.
Enzymes have a recommended name.
Enzymes may have a systematic name.
Enzymes may have one or more alternative names.
Enzymes may have a reaction.
Enzymes may have one or more comments.

Operations:
Initial load from IUBMB pages.
Initial load from Geneva flat file.

Insert new enzyme (Kirill, Sinead).

Approve all fields of enzyme (Sinead).

Change EC number, aka "transfer entry" (Sinead).

Delete enzyme (Sinead).

Display IUBMB view of enzyme.
Display IntEnz view of enzyme.
Display Geneva view of enzyme.
Find enzyme by EC number.
List all enzymes which belong to a certain subsubclass.
Find enzyme by partial match of one of the names.
Find enzyme by partial match of the reaction.
Find enzymes that have been approved after a given date.

*************************************************************************

THE VIEWS

One major point in the IntEnz project is to collect data from different
sources, and to provide a view on the data officially approved by the
IUBMB committee. 
Therefore we have to spend some resources on making sure that only approved 
data appears in the public IUBMB view. Secondly, we have to provide the 
infrastructure for a quick and streamlined approval mechanism.
We will have 3 distinct data views: IntEnz, NC-IUBMB and ENZYME.


IUBMB view
Only data inspected and approved by a member of the IUBMB committee is
seen in the IUBMB view. Certain fields are totally excluded, eg. 
SWISS-PROT protein accession numbers.

IntEnz view
This view contains also suggested data prior to approval. Furthermore,
there will be some fields, which are useful for the EBI/SIB/IntEnz, like
SWISS-PROT accession numbers.

ENZYME view
The SIB provides two flat files, enzyme.dat and enzclass.txt. As this was
the only readily available computer readable datasource, it gained a
certain status in the community. There are even some people who identify
these two flat files with the enzyme database.
Therefore, the ENZYME view should look like as similar as possible as the
existing flat files. As the IntEnz project progresses, we have to expect
that the view evolves closer to either the IUBMB view or the IntEnz view.

We have to be able to produce output in ENZYME flat file format. Kirill 
says it would be nice to be able to view every separate entry in ENZYME 
format during editing as well to ensure its maximal similarity to ENZYME. 
Every time Kirill needs to edit the ENZYME data, a report will be sent to 
Amos.

Brenda view
We don't need a BRENDA view as they have their own database. We will 
hopefully get some useful data from them with which we can enrich our
enzyme data. In exchange they can get our data and do the same with their 
database.

*************************************************************************
</pre>
   </section>
  </body>
</document>