<?xml version="1.0" encoding='iso-8859-1'?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="mdarsow@ebi.ac.uk">Michael Darsow</author>
    <title>About IntEnz</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="About IntEnz">
      <p>
      IntEnz is the name for the Integrated relational Enzyme database.
      IntEnz contains enzyme data
      that is curated and approved by the Nomenclature Committee of the International Union of
      Biochemistry and Molecular Biology
      (<a href="http://www.chem.qmul.ac.uk/iubmb/enzyme/">NC-IUBMB</a>).
      The goal is to create a single relational
      database containing enzyme data from three different sources:
      </p>
      <p/>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <a href="http://www.tcd.ie/">Trinity College Dublin</a> (TCD)
          maintains on behalf of the
          Nomenclature Committee of the International Union of Biochemistry and
          Molecular Biology
          (<a href="http://www.chem.qmul.ac.uk/iubmb/enzyme/">NC-IUBMB</a>) the
          Enzyme Classification list and is involved
          in many other aspects of biochemical nomenclature.<br/>
          In 2005 it has released an
          <a href="http://www.enzyme-database.org">enzyme database</a>
          based on MySQL, which seems to be the main source of data for BRENDA (see below).
        </li>

        <li>
          The <a href="http://www.isb-sib.ch/">Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics</a>
          (SIB) produces an
          Enzyme Nomenclature database (<a href="http://www.expasy.org/enzyme/">ENZYME</a>).
        </li>
        <li>
          The <a href="http://fileserver.bioinfo.nat.tu-bs.de/bioinf/">Technical
          University of Braunschweig</a> produces an enzyme function database
          (<a href="http://www.brenda-enzymes.org">BRENDA</a>),
          which contains a large amount of information on substrates, products, and inhibitors.
        </li>

      </ol>
      <p>
        The EBI has already implemented a relational database version storing the most up-to-date version of
        the Enzyme Classification list (1) which contains enzyme data curated and approved by NC-IUBMB.
        The relational database IntEnz is further populated by corresponding data from the Enzyme
        Classification list of SIB (2) and from BRENDA (3).<br/>
        The EBI has developed tools to maintain the database and allow propagation of new and
        updated biochemical terminology, which has been integrated into the database, to the other partners.
      </p>
      <p>
        The EBI also set up Internet services which initially facilitate text-based searches against the
        relational databases such as the protein sequence databases in
        <a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/uniprot">UniProt</a> (Swiss-Prot, TrEMBL, TrEMBLnew), the protein
        family signature database (<a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro/index.html">InterPro</a>),
        and Gene Ontology (<a href="http://www.geneontology.org/">GO</a>).
      </p>

    </section>
  </body>
</document>
