<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Export module</title>
		<author email="rafalcan@ebi.ac.uk">Rafael Alcántara</author>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="IntEnz export module">
            <div>
                The IntEnz export module dumps enzyme data in different formats,
                namely:
                <ul>
                    <li>IntEnzXML</li>
                    <li>Google sitemap: for use in the public web application</li>
                    <li>BioPAX</li>
                </ul>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                The main product of this application is the dump of IntEnz data in
                <b>XML format</b>. XML files are generated for every single active
                entry, and also for the entire IntEnz database.
                <br/>
                The structure of the XML is defined in a schema file (see the
                <a href="../tech_docs/specifications/intenzXml/intenzxml.html">specification</a>).
                JAXB has been used with this schema in order to generate
                the java classes in the uk.ac.ebi.intenz.tools.export.jaxb
                package.
            </div>
            <div>
                The export is usually done just before every IntEnz release,
                roughly every month. The XML schema is used for output validation.
                The files are then manually copied to make them accessible from
                <a href="ftp://ftp.ebi.ac.uk/pub/databases/intenz/xml">ftp://ftp.ebi.ac.uk/pub/databases/intenz/xml</a>.
            </div>
            <div>
                Currently, the following <i>flavours</i> of XML are available:
                <ul>
                    <li><b>XCHARS</b> (for eXtended CHARacterS): data
                        which includes XML markup in the
						IntEnz database is exported /as is/.
						Example: EC 1.1.1.100 has an accepted name
						'3-oxoacyl-<protein>acyl-carrier-protein</protein> reductase'. The
						corresponding XML will be:
<pre>
&lt;accepted_name view="INTENZ,IUBMB,SIB"&gt;
3-oxoacyl-&lt;xchars:protein&gt;acyl-carrier-protein&lt;/xchars:protein&gt; reductase
&lt;/accepted_name&gt;
</pre>
                        The <code>xchars</code> namespace is defined in
                        the root element of the XML file.
                        For more information on the XML markup used in
                        IntEnz, please refer to the
                        <a href="../xchars/index.html">XChars</a>
                        subproject.
					</li>
                    <li><b>ASCII</b>: the IntEnz fields with XML markup are translated into ASCII.
						Following the same example, the ASCII flavour of EC 1.1.1.100's accepted
						name will be:
<pre>
&lt;accepted_name view="INTENZ,IUBMB,SIB"&gt;
3-oxoacyl-[acyl-carrier-protein] reductase
&lt;/accepted_name&gt;
</pre>
					</li>
                </ul>
            </div>

            <div>
                Besides, with every IntEnz release, a new <b>sitemap</b> XML file
                (<code>sitemap.xml</code>) is generated to be used by
                <a href="http://www.google.com/webmasters/sitemaps">Google
                sitemaps</a> in order to make every IntEnz entry available to Google indexing.
                Other search engines accept this standard too.
            </div>

            <div>IntEnz is also dumped as one <a href="../biopax/index.html">BioPAX</a>
                file.
            </div>
        </section>
	</body>
</document>
