<?xml version="1.0" encoding='iso-8859-1'?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="kirill@ebi.ac.uk">Kirill Degtyarenko</author>
    <title>More about IntEnz</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Project: IntEnz">

<hr></hr>
<ol>
<li><a href="#introduction">Introduction</a> 
    <dl>
       <dd>1.1 <a href="#what">What is IntEnz?</a></dd> 
       <dd>1.2 <a href="#why">Why IntEnz?</a></dd>
       <dd>1.3 <a href="#funding">Funding</a></dd>
       <dd>1.4 <a href="#partners">Project partners</a></dd>
    </dl>
</li>

<li><a href="#annotation">IntEnz annotation</a>
    <dl>
       <dd>2.1 <a href="#general">General remarks</a></dd>
       <dd>2.2 <a href="#chebimapping">IntEnz to ChEBI mapping</a></dd>
       <dd>2.3 <a href="#sources">Sources of data</a></dd>
    </dl>
</li>

<li><a href="#products">IntEnz products</a>
    <dl>
       <dd>3.1 <a href="#relational">Relational database</a></dd>
       <dd>3.2 <a href="#html">HTML files</a></dd>
       <dd>3.3 <a href="#enzyme">ENZYME flat file</a></dd>
       <dd>3.4 <a href="#intenzxml">IntEnzXML</a></dd>
       <dd>3.5 <a href="#biopax">BioPAX export</a></dd>
       <dd>3.6 <a href="#curator_tool">Curator tool</a></dd>
    </dl>
</li>

</ol>

<hr></hr>
<a name="introduction"></a>
</section>

<section name="1. Introduction">
<a name="what"></a>
<subsection name="1.1 What is IntEnz?">
<p><a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/intenz/"><font
color="darkgreen"><b>IntEnz</b></font></a> is the name for the <font
color="darkgreen"><b>Int</b></font>egrated relational <font 
color="darkgreen"><b>Enz</b></font>yme database. IntEnz will contain
enzyme data approved by the Nomenclature Committee of the
<a href="http://www.iubmb.org/">International Union of Biochemistry and 
Molecular Biology</a> (NC-IUBMB).</p>
</subsection>

<a name="why"></a>
<subsection name="1.2 Why IntEnz?">
<p>
For many years, Amos Bairoch has been supporting the Enzyme 
Nomenclature database, appropriately called <a 
href="http://www.expasy.org/enzyme/"><b>ENZYME</b></a>. Indeed, this was 
the only electronic version of The Enzyme Nomenclature. For the big part 
of the bioinformatics communtity, ENZYME is <b>the</b> Enzyme 
Nomenclature. An obvious example is its use for <a 
href="http://www.uniprot.org">SWISS-PROT</a> annotation. However, in 
spite of containing the <b>data</b> from The Enzyme Nomenclature, it was 
never considered <b>an official publication</b> on The Enzyme Nomenclature 
(as opposed to, say, <i>Enzyme Nomenclature 1992</i>, Academic Press, San 
Diego). ENZYME exists as a plain ASCII text file.
</p>
<p>
The <a href="http://www.chem.qmw.ac.uk/iubmb/enzyme/"><b>Web Version of 
Enzyme Nomenclature</b></a> has been prepared by Gerry Moss and includes 
the complete contents of <i>Enzyme Nomenclature 1992</i> plus subsequent 
supplements and other changes. It is <b>official</b> and easy to navigate. 
However it is <b>not</b> a true database but a set of manually edited HTML
pages.</p>

<p>During their course of evolution, ENZYME, Enzyme Nomenclature and 
other databases containing enzyme-related information accumulated a number of
<b>discrepancies</b> in the data that are 
meant to be identical. These discrepancies could be anything e.g. typos, 
corrections, new data or their absence.
With more new data, it is becoming difficult to keep these sources in
sync.
</p>
<p>
The <b>goal</b> of the IntEnz project is to have a relational database that 
integrates all of the Enzyme Nomenclature.
</p>
</subsection>

<a name="funding"></a>
<subsection name="1.3 Funding">
<p>
After the BioBabel grant, no active funding is available to actively develop IntEnz.
None of the annotators funded by new Felics grant will be based at the EBI.
</p>
</subsection>

<a name="partners"></a>
<subsection name="1.4 Project partners">
<p>
<a href="http://www.isb-sib.ch/">SIB</a> (enzyme annotation).
</p>
</subsection>

</section>

<a name="annotation"></a>
<section name="2. IntEnz annotation">
<a name="general"></a>
<subsection name="2.1 General remarks">
<p>
Since most of the data in IntEnz will have 
"official" status, the mechanism of <b>approval</b> by NC-IUBMB had to be 
implemented. The data will enter IntEnz in one of two ways: 

<ul>
  <li><b>Legacy data</b> were loaded from the two pre-existing <a 
  href="#sources"><b>sources</b></a>. 
  As a rule, these do not have to be formally approved since the Enzyme 
  Classification List already <b>is</b> official. However, if there are 
  serious discrepancies between the sources and curator thinks the change 
  should be made to the master data, this may require an approval to 
  <b>suggested</b> change.</li>

  <li><b>New data</b> are entered directly to IntEnz via <b>IntEnz Web 
  Tool</b>. The tool, while prevents entering incomplete data, does not 
  check data validity. This data (whether it is a new entry or any 
  modification of an existing entry) will be considered <b>suggested</b>. 
  Suggested entries are visible to IntEnz curators but not to general 
  public. An NC-IUBMB member has priveleges to move the entry status from 
  <b>suggested</b> to <b>proposed</b>. Proposed entries or changes have to 
  be publicly available for at least <b>2 months</b> before the next 
  action is undertaken. This allows the scientific community to send the 
  feedback to the NC-IUBMB. After this, the entry could be either (i) 
  given <b>approved</b> status, (ii) <b>modified</b> and left as proposed 
  for some more time, or (iii) <b>rejected</b> completely.</li>
	</ul>
	</p>
</subsection>

<a name="chebimapping"></a>
<subsection name="2.2 IntEnz to ChEBI mapping">
<p>
Since IntEnz is one of the sources of terminology for
<a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/chebi/">ChEBI</a> database,
it was logical to link all the compound terms in reaction and cofactor fields of IntEnz
to corresponding ChEBI entries.
</p>
<p>
Initially, the <b>reaction</b> field in an IntEnz entry was a <b>free text</b>.
We aimed to improve quality of reaction data
in IntEnz and provide other databases with the new means of annotation by
<ul>
<li> Assigning public, stable, unique identifiers to reactions, thereby </li>
<li> Disentangling enzyme numbers and reactions </li>
<li> Removing redundancy </li>
</ul>
Partners from SIB and Uni Cologne expressed interest in this development.
As a result, the reaction database Rhea was created.
For more info, refer to the initial
<a href="../specifications/intenzReactions/reactions.html">reaction
specification</a> document and the <a href="http://rhea-ebi.sf.net">Rhea</a>
project website.
</p>


</subsection>

<a name="sources"></a>
<subsection name="2.3 Sources of data">
<p>
<ol>
  <li><a href="http://www.tcd.ie/">Trinity College Dublin</a> (TCD) 
  maintains on behalf of the NC-IUBMB the Enzyme Classification List (HTML 
  files).</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.isb-sib.ch/">Swiss Institute of 
  Bioinformatics</a> (SIB) produces ENZYME (ASCII file).</li>
	</ol>
	</p>
</subsection>

<a name="products"></a>
</section>

<section name="3. IntEnz products">

<a name="relational"></a>

<subsection name="3.1 Relational database">
<p>The main product of this project is a relational database, IntEnz,
which can be queried via the web interface.
The updated figures can be found in the
<a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/intenz/statistics.jsp"><i>statistics</i></a>
page.<br/>
Currently, we don't provide a downloadable database dump, which would
be an Oracle dump only usable by Oracle installations.
</p>
</subsection>

<a name="html"></a>
<subsection name="3.2 HTML files">
<p>The contents of the relational database can be browsed in form of 
HTML files in the <a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/intenz">IntEnz website</a>,
which show not only the IntEnz (integrated data) view, but
also the NC-IUBMB and SIB views.
</p>
</subsection>

<a name="enzyme"></a>
<subsection name="3.3 ENZYME flat file">
<p>
The contents of the relational database is exported every night in form of ASCII file
(enzyme_intenz.dat). It is essentially identical to the enzyme.dat flat file
prepared by SIB (found at <a href="ftp://ftp.expasy.org/databases/enzyme/">
ftp://ftp.expasy.org/databases/enzyme/</a>) which is used e.g. for UniProt anotation.
In fact, the enzyme_intenz.dat file is used by SIB curators as a basis for their work to
produce enzyme.dat. That way, enzyme data is curated just once using the IntEnz curator tool.
	</p>
	</subsection>

<a name="intenzxml"></a>
<subsection name="3.4 IntEnzXML">
<p>IntEnz data is exported as
<a href="ftp://ftp.ebi.ac.uk/pub/databases/intenz/xml">XML</a>,
following the provided
<a href="../specifications/intenzXml/intenzxml.html">specification</a>.</p>
</subsection>

<a name="biopax"></a>
<subsection name="3.5 BioPAX export">
<p>For compatibility with a broadly used standard, IntEnz is also exported as
a <a href="ftp://ftp.ebi.ac.uk/pub/databases/intenz/biopax">BioPAX</a> file.</p>
</subsection>

<a name="curator_tool"></a>
<subsection name="3.6 Curator tool">
<p>
Most of IntEnz annotation is done from outside of the EBI with the help of the
<a href="../webapp/intenz-curator/index.html">IntEnz Curator Tool</a>.
	</p>
</subsection>

</section>

</body>
</document>
